<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pious president to both kingdomes for a sacred covenant. Being an abstractive exposition by way of paraphrase upon the tenth chapter of Nehemiah, the 28, and 29 verses / by Daniell Svvift, Minister of the gospell of Iesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Swift, Daniel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E71_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7337</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873115</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873115</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125569</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125569)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 12:E71[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pious president to both kingdomes for a sacred covenant. Being an abstractive exposition by way of paraphrase upon the tenth chapter of Nehemiah, the 28, and 29 verses / by Daniell Svvift, Minister of the gospell of Iesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Swift, Daniel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Mary Okes, dwelling in little St. Bartholomewes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 16th".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Nehemiah X, 28-29 --  Paraphrases, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125569:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:125569:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Pious PRESIDENT To both KINGDOMES, For a Sacred COVENANT. Being an Abſtractive Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by way of Paraphraſe, upon the tenth Chapter of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> the 28, and 29. Verſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> DANIELL SVVIFT, <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Quidni dulce eruam ac ſalutare epulum Spiritus de ſterili et inſipida lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, tanquam granum de palea, de teſta nucleum, de oſſe medullam? <bibl>
                     <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> in Cant. ſermo. <hi>73.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Omnis panis nutrimentum aſſert ad ſalutem, aegris autem ſaepe inutilis, ſic et omnis ſcriptura munda mundis. <bibl>
                     <hi>Baſil.</hi> ad Chyl. de ſolitaria vita.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Seene and allowed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Mary Okes,</hi> dwelling in little St. Bartholomewes. 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:125569:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:125569:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, Right worthy and religious Patriots of their Countrie, <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of Eſſex, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> Earle of Warwick, and <hi>Ferdinando</hi> Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> renowned Inſtruments for diſappointing, and diſcouraging of the Romiſh and bloudy adverſaries of Gods ſacred Truth.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know you expect not flattering Titles, for (beſides the dint of Divine diſpleaſure) this were but to deſpite you with ſeeming Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. I deſire not with airy ambages to tickle your eares, I am ſure downe right truths make the deepeſt impreſſion upon honeſt hearts; neither doe I ſound the trumpet of applauſe; Heroicke actions, are glorious encomiums; Faithfulneſſe to God, the King, and Country, are the onely diademe of true Nobility, I may lay my hand upon my mouth, your owne workes ſhall praiſe you in the gates. There be many (Right Honourable) in theſe times, who care not to adventure their necks to advance themſelves, and matter not to hazard their ſoules, to ruine the Church; but as your Honours have publique ſpirits for the common good, ſo I am perſwaded Gods glory is your higheſt aimes, and to approve your ſelves before
<pb facs="tcp:125569:3"/> him, in all your underſtandings the chiefe endeavour of your ſoules: Let them looke at worldly acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as pleaſing cordialls; It is your Crowne, and will be the rejoycing of your hearts, that you keep a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence void of offence, both towards God, and towards his Saints; they are deceived who ſo highly eſtimate a little Laud, for hee onely whom God commendeth is approved; without, or againſt whom whoſoever deſires to be applauded ſhall not be defended when God judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him, nor delivered when God condemneth him. It is more then probable that nefarious wretches, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane creatures, by reproachfull ſpeeches, caſt fire-brands in your Honours faces; But what though? Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians make the beſt Triacle of venomous Serpents, <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> impoſtume was opened, and ſo healed by his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſword in the warrs. You are Wiſe Men, I hope you will make better uſe of your foes, then fooles of their friends: their aſperſions may prove doctrinall, teaching you to keepe cloſer (in a holy dependency) unto your God. I confeſſe you might be free from theſe, durſt you but abnegate or deſert the Truth; their revilings ſhall be your bleſſings: they are nocent, you innocent; they are deceived, they take you for ſuch as you are not; they have with the bellowes of Malignancy blowne up the coales of contention, they have enforced you (ſeeking by violence to depreſſe the power of godlineſſe) to take up armes in the defence of Chriſt, and his indeered ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ſurely it is a double injury to beate men cauſeleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly till they cry, and then to beate them for crying, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, and oppreſſion to kindle ſtrife, and then to cry out againſt it, as <hi>Athaliah</hi> cryed out of treaſon: offences will come, but there is no woe denounced againſt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb facs="tcp:125569:3"/> offended, but againſt thoſe by whom they come. Ride on Noble Lords, keepe your ſwords ſtill girt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout your thighs, let nothing diſcourage you, out-face the proud lookes of approaching adverſaries, their owne ſparkes ſhall further their owne burning, Gods wrath ſhall not end in your, but in their deſtruction. Your honours zeale for Religion, love to your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, courage in the publique cauſe, and mutuall agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in an holy Covenant, have hitherto ſpoke your ſincerity, declar'd your piety, and made you exemplary to them that ſhall ſucceed you. O now afreſh pluck up your ſpirits, quit your ſelves like Worthies in Iſrael, Chriſt like a man of warre leades out your forces, if our ſins interrupt not our mercies, the bloud of your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall ſpring up to the horſe bridles, and a glorious victory ſhall be yours. Pardon my boldneſſe in ſpeaking to your Honours, accept of my Mite though it be ſmall; I hope when you try it, you ſhall not finde it reprobate ſilver, but currant coyne. You have entred into an Oath, it is for God, the Goſpell, our Soveraigne, the Kingdome and your ſelves, I doubt not but you will ſet the Lord Jehovah in the proſecution of this ſacred Covenant, continually before your eyes, and by your zeale provoke many, adding fuell to the fire, and oyle unto the flame of their endeavours. The Lord proſper you in your great affaires, cover your heads in the day of battell, and goe forth before you in all your enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes, againſt the Romiſh and Anti-chriſtian Faction. So praies he, who remaines ever</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors humbly devoted, D. S.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>October</hi> 16. 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:125569:4"/>
            <head>To all that wiſh well to the Cauſe of God, and the Goſpell of Chriſt, in the two famous Kingdomes of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and in particular to his native Country-men, in the County of Leceiſter; <hi>D. S.</hi> wiſheth a firme Union in a ſacred Covenant, with a godly peace as the glorious effect thereof in this life, and eternall and everlaſting peace in the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Xpect not Complements, I am no Courtier, they are not for Chriſtians. looke not that I ſhould wind in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your affection by Rhetoricall expreſſions or ſmooth Suppariſi ations in the Preface; my intention is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>viz,</hi> to preſent unto you matter directory in the Treatiſe. Brethren my prayer to God and hearts deſire for you is, that you may be ſanctified in this life, and ſaved in the life to come. I beſeech you caſt your eyes upon Iſraels Oath, and ſee zeale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt impiety, reflect upon her Nobles and behold forwardneſſe to promote Gods glory, looke upon her Clergy with her whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and learne ſubmiſſion to a publique yet a pious injunction. Let her Covenant be your Preſident, and her obedience your incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Your Worthies intend nothing but Loyalty to his Majeſty and the continuall preſervation of your ſafety, helpe them with your pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, adhere to them in their ſacred Vow, let not your eſtates and lives be deare unto you for their ſakes, and ſee that you ſtart not from them, but ſtick to them, leſt you be found fighters againſt the Lord;
<pb facs="tcp:125569:4"/> Defend his Majeſties Royall perſon in authority (in the preſervation and defence of the true Religion and Liberties of the Kingdomes) to the laſt drop of bloud in your veines, that the world with your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences may beare witneſſe of your Loyalties, and that you are no Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Maintaine the truth of God with the priviledges of Parliament, though with the hazard of your lives: And for the underminers of Church and State, proſecute them untill you have brought them to receive a reward according to their de<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts. Thus doing in the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of your hearts, I doubt not (however dangers threaten you) but in the end you ſhall become glorious Conquerours through the power of the Lord Chriſt: I am perſwaded, in what I have done, I ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe ſome, but as <hi>Malis difplicere laudari eft,</hi> ſo my pur oſe was not to give content to malevolent perſons, but to approve my ſelfe to God and his hidden ones; for I ſhould be loath to ſpeake or write ought that Chriſt ſhould diſallow, he (truly) is that Maſter to whom every man ſtands or falls, and one good looke from him, is in ſtead of all acclamations to my ſelfe. The Lord direct you, preſerve you, and knit you firmely unto himſelfe. So prayeth he who reſts.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord Chriſt. D. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:125569:5"/>
            <head>The Contents, or the particular Obſervations. contained in this booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> MVtuall ſociety makes a ſweet harmony. <hi>Page 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The Clergy not exempted from civill Authority. <hi>pag. 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> A good Clergy, a Kingdomes felicity. <hi>page 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Every Chriſtian muſt be a porter to his owne heart. <hi>page 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> Wee muſt not hee fickle, conſtancy muſt crowne our actions. <hi>page 10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> Auſterity, and Magnanimity, become the profeſsors of Chriſtianity <hi>page 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> Sacred Covenants doe not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be ſeeme the moſt cheerefull ſpirits <hi>page 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> Worldly affaires muſt not ſhoulder out Chriſtian duties. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> Waſhing ſhould procede Covenanting. <hi>page 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> Meanneſſe of place and calling, debarres not any (by vowing) from bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelves to Religion. <hi>page 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> Godlineſſe in others ſhould be an attractive to our deſires. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> Other mens ſinns, muſt not make us turne our backs upon the pure Ordinances of God. <hi>page 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> Matrimoniall Leagues with Idolaters, an inlett to falſe worſhip, and a ſtrong barre to keepe out the power of godlineſſe. <hi>page 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> Covenanting Chriſtians, ſhould be couragious Chriſtians. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> Women not priviledged from ſpirituall vowes. <hi>pag. 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> Chriſtians ſhould be politicians. <hi>page 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> None exempted from a ſacred Vow. <hi>page 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> Examples of Superiours, ſtrong cords to draw on others unto holines. <hi>pag. 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19</hi> Pride becomes not noble Spirits. <hi>page 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20</hi> Inferiour perſons muſt accept of motions from their Nobles as motions from affectionate Brothers. <hi>Ibidem</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21</hi> Though imprecations and execrations be not uſuall, yet ſometimes t ey are very Lawfull. <hi>page 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22</hi> Wee may vow againſt ſin, wee may ſweare obedience unto God. <hi>page 38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23</hi> Gods Satutes the Chriſtians way. <hi>page 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>24</hi> The Law an effect of gods Love. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>25</hi> Our obedience must be univerſall: <hi>page 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26</hi> Sence of miſery under ſin and ſorrow with hope of mercy, puts the ſoule upon Covenants, yea ſure Covenants for nſicere and exact obedience to the God of Heaven. <hi>page 45</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:125569:5"/>
            <head>A pious Preſident to both Kingdomes, For a ſacred Covenant.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>NEHEMIAH 10.28, 29.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the reſt of the peop e the Priests, the Levites, the porters, the Singers, the Nethinims, and all they that had ſeparated themſelves from the people of the Land unto the Law of God, their wives, their Sons and their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, every one having knowledge, and having underſtanding.</p>
                  <p>They clave to their Brethren the Nobles, and entred into a curſe, and into an oath to walke in Gods Law, which was given by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the ſervant of God, and to obſerve, and doe all the Commandements of the Lord our God, his ſtatutes, and his judgements.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe Verſes you have the Commons of Iſrael, joyning with their Nobles in a firme covenant to the Lord Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah: wherein you may take notice
<list>
                  <item>Firſt of the perſons who are deſcribed.
<list>
                        <item>Firſt generally
<list>
                              <item>The reſt of the people</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Secondly more particularly.
<list>
                              <item>1 The Prieſt that offered Sacrifice.</item>
                              <item>2 The Levits that inſtructed the people</item>
                              <item>3 The porters that kept the doores of the Sanctuary.</item>
                              <item>4 The Singers.</item>
                              <item>5 The Nethinims, that drew water for the houſe of the Lord.</item>
                              <item>6 All that had ſeparated themſelves from the people of the land, unto the Law of God, their wives, their ſonnes and their daughters, every one having knowledge and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly of their actions.
<list>
                        <item>They clave to their brethren the Nobles.</item>
                        <item>They entered into a curſe and into an Oath, to walke in Gods Law, &amp;c.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>And the reſt of the people.</q>
            <p>Mutuall ſociety cauſeth a pleaſing and melodious harmony;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervation.</hi> Iſraels mutual communion.</note> they doe not harpe upon the jarring ſtrings of diſtempered affections,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:125569:6"/> their tongues utter their minds; their expreſſions and intentions are not diſſonant, but conſonant one with another; they doe not onely like the Iron and the clay in the toes of <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> Image, cleave together, but they are faſt cemented, yea incorporated one into another: now as in a bed of ſpices there is a fragrancy in all their graces, their vertues like ſweet perfumes, upon burning coales are become communicative, all that are neare them, may receive comfort and refreſhing from them; they are not every man for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, they are all in common; they halt not betwixt two opinions; they have not a heart and a heart like <hi>Ephraine;</hi> they uphold Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian communion, they will not forſake the aſſembly of the Saints; they have all ſet their heart with their brethren the Nobles to ſeeke the Lord God of Iſraell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Application.</note>Doth not Unity make happy, and perpetuate a people? this is that precious oyntment, that ran downe from <hi>Aarons</hi> beard to the skirts of his garment, this is like the dew of Hermon deſcending upon the mountaines of Sion: for where this is; the Lord comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his bleſſing. Why doe not we then of this Nation, labour to become like Jeruſalem, as a City at unity within our ſelves? It is civill diſcord that demoliſhes and deſtroyes the very being of a Common-wealth, for as he that bleeds inwardly is in the greateſt danger, ſo <hi>a Kingdome divided againſt it ſelfe, cannot ſtand.</hi> The ſpirit of Aegypt never failed in the middeſt of her, untill the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians fought againſt the Egyptians;<note place="margin">Iſi. 10 2, 3.</note> neither did the Philiſtims melt like ſnow againſt the Sunne, untill ſuch time as they ſheathed their ſwords in one anothers bowells: O let it not be told in Gath, nor publiſhed in Askelon. that England by civill diſtention is the cauſe of her owne ruine: But oh my belly, my belly, I am pained at the very heart: I heare the ſound of the Trumpet, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larme for the warre: what, ſhall I not now with mourning and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting <hi>Ieremy,</hi> weepe day and night for the ſlaine of the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Sion? O that our rents and diviſions were cloſed, that the bloud of Chriſtians, religious and well-affected perſons, might no longer (as water that is ſpilt upon the ground) bee ſhed amongſt us. O let us yet, though it be late, (for better late thrive then never) ſet upon ſome courſe, whereby the ſluces of wrath may bee let downe, the currents of juſtice may be ſtopt, and the fire of Gods
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:125569:6"/> jealouſie may be extinguiſht amongſt us; why ſhould wee carry more fewell to the fire, and more oyle unto the flame of the Lords dreadfull vengeance through want of concord amongſt our ſelves? Let us pray, yea contend with God in prayer for the peace of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem: we may know that none ſhall proſper but they that love her, and can we love her and not pray for her? For our brethren and companions ſake, let us ſay, peace be within her walls, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the houſe of the Lord our God, let us ſeeke to doe her good: Now that we may doe thus we all can tell how that united forces are the ſtrongeſt, and that a three-fold cord is not eaſily broken;<note place="margin">Vis unita for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior.</note> therefore let us endeavour to keepe the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace. If the prayers of one <hi>Moſes</hi> could ſuppreſſe the Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites; O how ſoone then would a Land of praying Chriſtians pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate the Heavens, and cauſe our enemies to fall before us?<note place="margin">Cant. 6.9.</note> why doe we ſtand ſtill divided? let us like Chriſts Dove become but one, that the daughters that ſee us may powre out their bleſſing upon us. Give me leave to make uſe of <hi>Pauls</hi> requeſt to the Church of Corinth, and beſeech you brethren by the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that we may once all ſpeake the ſame thing, and that there may be no ſchiſmes amongſt us, but that we may be perfectly joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgement. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiâ paruae res creſcunt,</hi> concord will cauſe a growth, not onely of ſtrength, but of many other good things amongſt us. Unanimouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now let us concurre together, let us every man for himſelfe, and all of us one with another, ingage our ſpirits by promiſe, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige our ſoules by a ſolemne vow to the Lord of Heaven; thus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we ſhall eſtabliſh a bleſſed communion, and this wee cannot doe, unleſſe in covenant with theſe repenting Iſraelites wee adhere unto our brethren our Nobles.<note place="margin">The Prieſts and Levites. <hi>Obſervat.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Prieſts and Levites were chiefe officers in the Temple, they ſtand not upon their tip-toes, pleading immunity from civill authority; they apprehend not themſelves diſcharged of,<note place="margin">The Clergy not exempted from civill au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</note> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from their due allegiance. God hath not ſaid by them Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces rule, but by him they reigne and decree juſtice. It was but fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting they ſhould expreſſe ſubmiſſion, for as every ſoule muſt bee ſubject to the higher powers, ſo I am ſure it is not ſafe for a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but dangerous to a ſtate, where the Croſiers receive not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:125569:7"/> from the Regall ſword. Theſe worthies of Iſrael having ſet forth their Ordinance for a covenant with God, this Leviticall Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, like the Romiſh faction, cry not up freedome, and forthwith declaime againſt them; they expreſſe their yeilding by their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent obeying, they contradict not; theſe you ſee aſwell as others cleave unto their brethren the Nobles.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Obſervat. A good Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes felicity.</note>Miniſters ſhould be Ring-leaders not to rebellion, but ſubmiſſion, not to prophaneneſſe, but to conſcientious and ſincere obſervance, theſe Prieſts and Levites are in their due poſture, they are not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries to the Land of <hi>Iudah,</hi> they are not fomenters of jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies in their peoples eares, they condeſcend in their owne perſons to prevent ſuſpitious betwixt the Nobles and the Commons: for what is jealouſie? it is as unſatiable as the grave; it is the greateſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill to a Common-wealth, and the deadlieſt enemy, as to affection, ſo to ſubmiſſive obedience. The Prieſts in the time of the Law pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented oblations 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.28. and burnt incenſe before the Lord; theſe (conſidering that obedience is better than ſacrifice, and that God layes more clayme to the living than to the dead,) joyne with their worthies, obſerve the Ordinance, take the Covenant, and in theſe as a living burnt offering give up themſelves to God. The Levites expounded the Law, diſplayed the ſacred Oracles, in things ſpiritual, inſtructed the congregations, ſecular affairs were not the ſubject matter of their imployments; they ſtudied Theologie, not policy, the Art of teaching rather than the Art of ruling, I am ſure that thus it was with theſe of the Tribe of Levi: for they brake not the Covenant, <hi>Malach.</hi> 2.8. They teach holineſſe, and they practiſe piety: they are not like wolves in ſheepes ſkins, palliating cruelty under the habit of meekeneſſe, their doctrine is a light, and their lives are a lampe, that like wiſe builders they ſet up godlineſſe, and like ſavoury ſalt, ſeaſon the hearts of their hearers. O Iſrael it was thy happineſſe to have ſuch Levites, it hath bin, and I feare me in ſome meaſure yet is our miſery, to want ſuch Leaders; dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe diſcovers no dangers, and if the blind lead the blind, they both fall into the ditch.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Application.</note>The time was when old <hi>Ely</hi> heard of evill dealing in the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, how <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehas</hi> his ſacrificing ſonnes made the Lords people to tranſgreſſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.23.24. Thus did the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:125569:7"/> watch-men of <hi>Iudah,</hi> in ſtead of knocking of the fingers,<note place="margin">Quantum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitioſa eſt ad ſequentium lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumuina prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſiti, in tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum contrà uti le eſt, et ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, cum ſe Epiſiopus per firmamentum fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e fratribut inultandum, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet. Cyprian Lib <hi>3.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>21</hi> Omnium fel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rum promittunt licentiam et quaſi vexillum gerunt ad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandam omnem ſpeciim nequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Calvin. Cur pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ata populi comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere à cuatur niſiquia pecca a delinquenitium ſove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, <hi>Grego. Homel. 17</hi> Omnino prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem ſe eſſe noverit, quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eſt ille, qui vitae quae libet in ia hanc domum conatur indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, Bernard.</note> ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked, when by their owne example (crying, wee will powre forth wine, and fill our ſelves with ſtrong drinke) <hi>Eſay</hi> 56.12. They gave them incouragement in their nefarious courſes. And was it not becauſe of this, that they propheſied in <hi>Baal,</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Iſrael to erre, committed adultery, walkt in lies, confirmed men in their helliſh practiſes, and not ſuffering them to returne, made them as Sodome, and as the Inhabitants of Gomorrah before the Lord. That made <hi>Ieremy</hi> in a dolefull lamentation give out this expreſſion, <hi>that his very heart was broken,</hi> Ier. 23.9.13.14. But theſe mentioned by <hi>Nehemiah</hi> are of another temper, they doe not eate of the ſins of the people by being foſter fathers to their filthy vices; theſe doe not build with their doctrine, and pull downe by their practiſe, the light of their converſations is now become ſo fulgent, that others may behold them for their imitation; they doe not ſeeke to innovate Religion, erect novelties, and advance ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious vanities, as ſometimes <hi>Vrijah</hi> the Prieſt did, who built an Altar according to all that <hi>Ahaz</hi> had ſent from Damaſcus. 2 Kings 16.11. nay theſe reſolve too, to bid adue to Idolatry, to demoliſh ſuperſtition, and not to ſtand any longer guilty of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall treaſon, by upholding wickedneſſe in Gilgall, I might have ſaid Bethel, the houſe of the Lord. For as they goe before the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the covenant, affording them their examples for their incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement; ſo by covenant they bind themſelves for ever from all idle or idolizing worſhip, to obſerve &amp; do all the Commandements of God; thus they animate the children of Zion, going before them in the meanes of ſanctification, and thus they ſeeke not to eſtabliſh, but to depreſſe iniquity by a law.</p>
            <p>Hearken to me yee that have deviated from the ſonnes of <hi>Levi,</hi> you ſtile your ſelves Prieſts, and lay claime to the office, as if God had onely intayled the Prieſt-hood upon you; what will you yet be as a ſnare on <hi>Mizpah,</hi> and as a net ſpread upon <hi>Tabor?</hi> Hoſ. 5.1. will you yet as troopes of Robbers wait for a man, murder in the way, and that by conſent? Hoſ. 6.9. why doe you ſtill deſire to ſell the righteous for ſilver, to turne aſide the way of the meeke, and to drinke the wine of the condemned, or of good men fined in the houſe of your God? Amos 2.6.7.8. See, ſee, theſe Prieſts, the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:125569:8"/> ſubject of our diſcourſe read another lecture to your ſoules: Theſe breath not out threatnings againſt the Church, they rather cry out, what ſhall we doe for the Church? theſe are not cruell thirſting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bloud, the precious bloud of Gods indeered ones; their armes and their hearts are both open, not onely with tender imbrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to receive them, but to ſupport them; it doeth not vexe them that they are zealous for the Lord, neither doe they ſeeke to finde them or puniſh them for the ſtrict ſervice of their God; their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe to forſake wickedneſſe is the joy of their ſpirits, their preciſeneſſe in the way of holineſſe is as marrow to their bones, and their covenant for new obedience is that they further by their owne preſident. Theſe are not diſmayed with the thoughts of more paines unto themſelves, if thus they covenant to keepe ſtrictly all the ſtatutes of the Lord, they prize Gods mercy to the people before their toyle, and their hearers wellfare before their labour, for though never ſo much ſedulity may be expected from them,<note place="margin">Non in verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſplendore, ſed in operum virtute, praedi candi fiductam ponant, non vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus delectem, tur populi ac clamantis, ſed ſterihu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nec plauſum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedeat, ſed gem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. proſ. per, Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>23.</hi> vitacontemplat. A Paſtore exi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>getur, quicquid perinertiam non cuſtoditur Cypiran, de ſing. Cleric.</note> they will not flinch off but in the preſent covenant adhere unto them; Before like <hi>Herod</hi> they ſolaced themſelves in their peoples accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations; now their teares and their prayers are prime pleaſures to their ſoules; time was, when breaking the bonds of doctrine, and knapping aſunder the cords of diſcipline was their delight, now their fulgency in vertue demonſtrated by their reſoluteneſſe for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act obedience is the muſick in their eares, the hony in their mouthes, and the very rejoycing of their hearts; They know they muſt give account, for their peoples ſoules, and that if they periſh, God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them at their hands; they give them up therefore now by vow unto the Lord, and in this their ſurrender they ſeeme to ſay, Lord here we are, and all our people the children that thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto us. They are not ignorant that much trouble from them who are without may ariſe by reaſon of this covenant: they feare no colours, they put on their auditors, they are reſolved to eat of the ſame diſh, to taſte of the ſame ſauce, and if they ſuffer, to ſuffer with them, this muſt needs hearten them for couragious Souldiers, goe not weeping nor ſighing after their Commanders. It may bee they apprehend ſome malevolent and malignant creatures to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people, ready like ſcab'd ſheepe to infect the flock, like <hi>Peters</hi> falſe Prophets by damnable hereſies laying aſperſions upon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:125569:8"/> the truth, and like cunning and crafty ſeducers uſing all diligence to make them the divells Proſelytes like themſelves: Theſe have not their favourable aſpect, theſe have not their hearts, their hands, their eſtates; theſe are caſhiered; the yeilding, the mourning, yet the reſolving Iſraelites have their affections, amongſt theſe onely they are perſonally preſent, with theſe they ſide, and to theſe they joyne in covenant with the Lord: They are not as time ſerving Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants, onely reſpective to great men, their deportment is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, they take care for the poore aſwell as the rich, it is not their owne preferment, but every mans wellfare that they looke for. Therefore as by their forwardneſſe they excite all, ſo by their actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all performance withall; they ſhew their tender of the happineſſe and proſperity of all. Learne then from theſe Prieſts and Levites, I beſeech you my Brethren, I ſtile you ſo, becauſe I would have you ſo: Firſt,<note place="margin">Directions to Miniſters.</note> not to thinke it ſtrange that others with you run not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame exceſſe of riot, that they keepe not out of Covenant aſwell as your ſelves, they ſee their miſery, and this to be their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, and they know that your non-ſeeing, or elſe perverſe ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of your owne eſtates, can be no healing plaiſters to their ſoules. It behoves every man to looke to his owne ſtanding, and to bee carefull to prevent his owne damnation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Doe not pine the Lords people through deſtructive ignorance, doe not conceale the benefit of a ſacred Covenant from the eye of their ſpirits, left God complaine that his people periſh, for lacke of knowledge, and lay the guilt of their bloud upon your ſoules.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, doe not pernitiouſly poyſon by corrupt principles thoſe that are your hearers, teach not exorbitant errors for ſacred truthes, doe not through airy ambages and falſe gloſſes ſteale away their affections, and make them heartleſſe to holy vowes: thus doing you ſhall ſtill keepe them out of the way, cauſe them to ſtumble at the Law, and in the end be charged your ſelves for corrupting the covenant of <hi>Levi,</hi> Malach. 2.8.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, doe not over-lade your faint and your feeble brethren, with the onerous burthens of unneceſſary things, theſe burthens may lye heavy upon their ſhoulders, they will caſe themſelves by covenant,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.40.</note> but as you ſhall have the practiſe of the Primitive times
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:125569:9"/> to paſſe a ſentence condemnatory upon you, Act. 15.10.28. ſo one day they like Scorpions will ſting your conſciences, when Chriſts woe like a Hue and Cry ſhall arreſt your ſoules. Theſe Paſtors ſtand not upon circumſtance, they looke to the ſubſtance, the pious vow that they and their people muſt make to God.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, be examples to your flocks in word, in converſation and in charity. 1 Tim. 4.12. Let your words utter the Will of Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah, your converſations teſtifie the uprightneſſe of your hearts and your charity witneſſe that in all meanes and wayes you ſeeke the ſalvation of their poore ſoules; ſpeake you to them, that they may ſpeake from you to themſelves, ſaying, what have we done? be as lights ſet upon a Hill, that thoſe who are without may be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by your lives: Love with pitty, perſwade them, wooe them, win them, yea and becauſe that corroſives are ſometimes both more needfull and helpefull then mild and pleaſing cordialls; reprove them, rebuke them, drive them by the ſight of ſin, with your owne preſident, to ſee a neceſſity, as a chiefe preſervative, of an eſpeciall covenant, that ſo they being ingaged to God, and in that ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment apprehenſive of their owne mercy, they may rejoyce, that though they were brands, they are now pluckt out of the fire, that though they were aliens to God, yet now by a religious co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant they have entered into a ſweet communion with the Lord.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, you are, or at leaſt ſhould be, the Chariots and the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Iſrael, carry them up ſpeedily, with a ſwift motion, by your prayers to Heaven; looke upon our crying ſins with a bleeding heart, for the Vine of England is as the Vine of Sodome, and the grapes of our Nation doe wholly reſemble the cluſters of Gomorrah) view our lamentable diſtractions with mournefull affections; ſee, ſee, wrath is gone forth, and the plague is begun; Juſtice is incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and we turne our backes upon our adverſaries; jealouſie is kindled, and the ſword is almoſt drunke with the bloud of the ſlaine; your neighbours houſes are on fire, for ſhame ſit not ſtill, bring prayers as waters, and poure them on as faſt as you can, that you may ſlake the burnings; doe not ſtand gazing about you, it is time for you to be up, and be doing, unleſſe you meane that all our ſoules ſhall faint becauſe of the murderers; the banners of Gods diſpleaſure are diſplayed, and now like a man of warre hee hath
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:125569:9"/> begun to ſtrike the ſtroake, yea the ſword already reacheth to the very heart: O doeth not our land cry out as ſometime Hieruſalem did, woe is come upon me becauſe that I have ſinned, doth ſhee not bemoane her ſelfe unto you daily, asking you if you have no pitty, if your hearts bee wholly ſhut up in obduracy? me thinkes theſe expreſſions ſhould ſet you to your prayers; oh then if you will be accounted the Miniſters of the Lord, weepe between the Porch and the Altar, and ſay, <hi>Spare thy people O Lord;</hi> queſtionleſſe theſe Prieſts joyned with their Nobles as well in prayers as in covenant for the Church.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, be not averſe to take this binding and obliging vow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon your ſelves, theſe Prieſts and Levites have obſerved its equity, taken notice of its neceſſity, and found it the ſole remedy for the curing of their ſores, they doe not ſcruple it; our caſe is as bad if not worſe then theirs, why are you ſhie, bind your ſelves with a curſe, and an oath with the people to ſtand out againſt Popery, and in ſpirit and truth to ſerve the Lord. This will be a good incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to your hearers, if you goe before, they will the willinglier fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after; your forwardneſſe will make many to come in, who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwaies, it may be, will ſtill ſtand out to lift up their hands againſt Heaven; you ſee this in effect in theſe Prieſts, and in this people, who in this very particular <hi>Cleave unto their brethren the Nobles.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>The Porters.</q>
            <p>A Potter is a Doore-keeper which hath authority to admit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> 1. Every Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an a porter to his own heart.</note> and let in and out of the houſe where his charge is, ſuch were <hi>Obed Edom</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ieduthun,</hi> and <hi>Hoſah</hi> in the daies of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> to the houſe of the Lord, 1 Chr. 16.38. Theſe were to let in the Iewes not they that contemned their worſhip, theſe were to keep out the uncleane, not they that were cleanſed according to the Sanctuary; the true Iſraelites were to be admitted, but the idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous heathens were by them to be excluded. Every Chriſtian muſt be a Porter to his owne heart; whatſoever he is that covenants with God, muſt looke narrowiy to himſelfe, have a watchfull eye over his ſpirit, and with all diligence keepe his ſoule, that wicked luſts, vile affections, and vaine thoughts get not in at the doore of his heart; theſe will make hubbubs in this ſpirituall Temple, theſe will diſturb and ſtrike with violence at the ſanctifying motions of the bleſſed Spirit; theſe like the ſtrong man armed, will ſo keepe poſſeſſion, that godlineſſe ſhall get no entrance, without ſtrugling and much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:125569:10"/> theſe are ill gueſts, where they come in they pretend friendſhip, but intend miſchiefe, they pay no reckoning, they are cheaters, they doe but deceive the creature with the counterfeit ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of ſinfull pleaſures; theſe are like drunken and deboyſt ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, who by vomit eaſing their ſtomacks, leave nothing but ſtinch, loathſome filth, and noyſome ſavours in the roome behind them. A Sparrow purſued by a Hawk fled into the boſome of <hi>Xenocrates,</hi> he refuſed to put it out, ſaying it is a diſhoneſt thing to betray a gueſt:<note place="margin">D ogen. in vit.</note> Doe not thou thus kindly deale with thy ſins, it is not inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity to refuſe them; it is a piece of the beſt policy forth-with to expell them. Let luſts accuſe thee of diſcourteſie, better they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine than thou bleed, for ſin is the ſoules murderer; therefore, O Hieruſalem, waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe, that thou maiſt be ſaved; how long ſhall thy ſoule like an Inne, and thy heart like a Harlot harbour corruption.</p>
            <q>We muſt not be fickle, conſtancy muſt crowne our actions.</q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> 2.</note>POrters are continuall attendants, they wait daily at the Gates, &amp; depart not from their ſervice, 2 Chro. 35.15. we muſt not be fickle, like <hi>Lots</hi> wife; we muſt not looke back to Sodome, there muſt be conſtancy in all our vowes, it is diſhoneſty with man, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety to breake with the Lord; thou muſt not vow and not pay, but as without delaies, ſo conſtantly thou muſt pay thy vowes. Call to mind thy firſt vow, remember all thy promiſes, and ſelfe engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto God in the late daies of thy humiliation, be not unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, doe not like a broken bow ſtart from them, thou canſt never loſe by keeping touch with the Lord of Heaven. Theſe <hi>Porters</hi> leave not their Places becauſe of a covenant, like idle drones, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſeers, and atheiſticall wretches they ſteale not away, leave their charge, take up armes, and deſert their Nobles, becauſe of a ſtrict tye unto Gods ſervice: They were Porters before, and they are Porters ſtill; now they are content to doe more than formerly they did, they will keep the doore of the Temple; and withall looke carefully to the gate of their owne heart, leſt at any time it ſhould run out, and depart from the living God. They are not friends to them that hate peace, favourites to them that delight in warre, they take no pleaſure in the tents of Kedar, they deſire yet to be doore-keepers in the houſe of the Lord, for now as <hi>Porters</hi> they take the covenant with their Nobles.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:125569:10"/>
            <q>Auſterity and magnanimity become the Profeſſors of Christianity.</q>
            <p>POrters for the moſt part are men of a ſterne countenance,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> 3.</note> men of ſtrength, and men of couragious ſpirits, for that ſometimes they may meet with reſiſtance. Auſterity and magnanimity doe well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the profeſſors of Chriſtianity; we cannot looke too ſternely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon our luſts, we cannot be too ſtrong, too couragious, and too ſevere in keeping downe, and in the conſtant ſuppreſſion of our wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. The Divell, the world, and our owne baſe hearts would keepe us from pious and religious vowes, we have need of more then an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſtrength to repell theſe fiery darts, leſt by hindering our cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, they give a mortiferous and a deadly blow unto our ſoules. Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, be perſwaded then to watch, to ſtand faſt in the faith,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 16.13</note> to quit you like men, to be ſtrong, and not to forſake or refuſe the liberty where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Chriſt would make you free, take heed that you doe not againe intangle your ſelves with the yoke of bondage: Therefore, that you may walk worthy of the Lord, unto all pleaſing, being fruitfull in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very good worke, I pray that you may be ſtrengthned with all might, according to his glorious power, unto all patience, and long ſuffering, with joyfulneſſe. It is likely, theſe men were auſtere in their place re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute in their office, and ſtout towards all that oppoſed them in the execution of their charge; yet you ſee in this action, here is no gaine-ſaying no reſiſting, no withſtanding, they are very tractable, very flexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to a holy vow. When God diſplayes the excellency, neceſſity, and efficacy of a ſacred Covenant to the eye of mens ſoules, Lions ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Lambs, wolves ſhall become ſheep, and Leopards ſhall be as Kids before the Lord.</p>
            <q>The Singers.</q>
            <p>SIngers were ſuch as played upon muſicall Inſtruments,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> 4.</note> who with Trumpets and Cymbals ſet forth the praiſe of God; hence it is, that ſome interpreters give out the word Muſitians, not Singers in the text. Singing is no Embleme of ſadneſſe, it denotes cheerfulneſſe, it betokens alacrity, therefore well ſaid St. <hi>Iames, If any be merry, let him ſing Pſalmes.</hi> Sacred covenanes doe not unbeſeeme the moſt cheerefull ſpirits; expreſſions of joy, ariſing from gladneſſe of heart, may be concomitants in a Chriſtians vowes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> Sacred Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants doe not unbeſeeme the moſt cheerefull ſpirits.</note> This Oath ordained and confirmed by their Worthies, doth not marre their muſick, they can ſtill be Singers, and yet covenanters with their Nobles; they ſee it is the way for pacification, the onely Antidote to prevent deſtruction, and the ſole remedy to cure their miſery; the thoughts of it, lightens their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:125569:11"/> hearts, vivifies their ſpirits, and cauſeth them ſo to perke up the head, that now with thankeſgiving they can take their vow before the Lord, well (beloved) Gods vowes are upon us, wee are now to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with our God, let us by a cheerefull acceptance ſet forth his praiſe. Pſal. 56.12. Iehovah requires a cheerefull giver; Shall we not therefore ſing praiſe to his name for ever, that we may daily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme our vowes Pſal. 61.8. But who are we that ſhould be able willingly after this ſort to offer before the Lord? 1 Chro. 29.14.</p>
            <q>The Nethinims</q>
            <p>THe Nethinims were ſuch as carried water for the uſe of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, this they drew for the Congregation and for the Altar of the Lord. <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 9.27. The labour and drudgery of their outward callings doth not ſo drinke up their time, but the expreſſe carefullneſſe to lay hold of opportunity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> Worldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>res ſhould not ſhoulder out chriſtian duties.</note> for working out of their owne ſalvations. Worldly buſines muſt not ſhoulder out Godlineſſe; Throng in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall affaires will not excuſe us from ſprituall imployments, wee muſt ſet ſeaſons apart for God, domeſtique occaſions muſt not ſteale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our hearts. I and my Houſhold ſaith <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> will ſerve the Lord. It is an ill trouble in earthly matters, or about many things that keepes thee thy children, or thy ſervants from ſitting at the feet of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Obſervat.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The water that the <hi>Nethinims</hi> brought unto the Sanctuary was for cleanſing, they are inſtruments in purging of the Temple, and they are now by cloſing in this covenant coe-workers with God for the purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their owne ſoules; Let us waſh our hands in innocency be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee compaſſe the Altar, let us rub off the ſoyle of ſin, and then fall upon our ſpiritual imployments; wee muſt waſh us and make us cleane from the evill of our doings, before God and our ſoules by way of Covenant can converſe together. Draw water out of the well of thy heart, I weane the teares of contrition, drench thy ſoule in them, and powre them out abundantly before the Lord, neither ſtay here, but that thy conſcience may be cleanſed from dead workes, carry thy ſoule with her ſorrow to that fountaine that is ſet open for the houſe of <hi>David</hi> and inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> O rince it, rince it tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly in thoſe clear ſtreames of Chriſts precious bloud, that ſo thou mayſt ſtand ſpotleſſe, pure and blameleſſe at the bar of juſtice. In the time of the Law uncleanneſſe was cured by waſhing, for uncleane touchings, the parties waſhed their cloathes Levit. 11.40. for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane iſſues, they waſht theſmelves and their cloathes, Levit. 15.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:125569:11"/> 13. But for the uncleannes of leproſy, they waſht themſelvs, their cloths, ſhaved off all their haire, and ſtayed 7 dayes without the Campe, Levit. 14.8.9. Dear brethren our pollution is of the worſt kind, it is no other then the leproſie of ſin that wee are infected with, as it hath ſpread it ſelfe all over us, ſo it hath made our whole man ſubject to the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full curſe of Allmighty God. Rom. 5.18. Doth any thing proceed from us, but what is foule and damnable? Are not our splendid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances glittering ſins, and our moſt glorious actions as menſtruous ragges? doe wee touch any thing that wee taint not? where come we that wee leave not an ill ſent behind us? Let us all then generally apply water to our foule parts, ſcoure off the ſcurfe of prophaneneſſe, and free our ſelves of all filthyneſſe of fleſh and ſpirit whatſoever; Take the Apoſtles advice, cleanſe your hands you ſinners,<note place="margin">Jam. 4.8.9.</note> and purifie your hearts you double minded, bee afflicted, mourne and weepe, let your laughter bee turned into mourning, and your joy to heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, bee yee humbled, and make a holy Covenant with your God.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Nethinims were but water bearers, they had one of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Offices appertaining to the Temple,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> 3 Meanneſſe of place and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling debarres not any by vowing from binding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> yet theſe you ſee come into covenant with their Nobles. Meanneſſe of place and calling debarres not any by vowing, from binding themſelves to Religion. A poore Sacrifice in the time of the Law received acceptance, where a rich one could not be brought; the widowes mite had its welcome aſwell as the treaſure of the wealthy; A Nethinim in his place may bee as deare to God as a Prieſt; with God there is no reſpect of perſons, he that worketh righteouſneſſe is accepted with him; Therefore you that are meane, you that are deſpicable in the eye of the world, be not afraid, let not your meaneneſſe and poverty diſmay you, come in if you be for God, your Nobles are brethren, therefore joyne with them in covenant before the Lord.</p>
            <q>And all that had ſeparated &amp;c.</q>
            <p>They doe not ſeparate from them becauſe they are more zealous in profeſſion, more heavenly in affection, and more ſtrict in their converſation then themſelves, they love the brotherhood, they make much of them that feare the Lord, they deſert onely the Heathen, you ſee they approve of, and ſtand well affected to chriſtian communion. They doe not ſay of their fellow worſhippers as <hi>Ahab</hi> ſaid of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caiah,</hi> wee hate them, we heare of no good to us from them; or as it was ſaid of <hi>Cajus Sejus,</hi> they are good honeſt men, but onely they are Chriſtians, or as ſome vile Caytiffes of our times, wee like the men
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:125569:12"/> well, but we will not come amongſt them for they are preciſians, they are not men for our company, they are auſtere in their carriage, wee and they cannot hit it, for they are zelots in Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> 1. Others God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines ſhould be our Attractive.</note>Godlineſſe in others ſhould be the attractive to our deſires, and the Loadſtone to draw, not to eſtrange our affections, <hi>Davids</hi> delight was in them that excelled in vertue, but in our times it is a Capitall crime to be truly religious, the very name of an honeſt man who makes conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his wayes is now growne odious. I wiſh there were leſſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipathy, and more Sympathy, that Sympathy might once breed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie amongſt us.</p>
            <p>They doe not ſeparate from them of their owne Nation, and of their owne Religion, but from the people of the Lands, ſuch with whom God had denied them communion, <hi>viz.</hi> Idolatrous Heathens, queſtionleſſe there were many formall perſons, many prophane creatures and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious wretches amongſt themſelves; yet becauſe theſe are dayly in the Temple, they renounce not the aſſemblies, they turne not their backs upon the Ordinance, like peeuiſh or pettiſh children they throw not away the covenant, becauſe theſe or at leaſt many of theſe are likely to take it with them; wheras it is ſaid all they that had ſeparated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves &amp;c. it gives us to underſtand that there were ſome that had not ſeparated themſelves; Here were diviſions, yet for ought I can find, they that were ſeparated,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> 2. Other mens ſins muſt not make us turne our backs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the pure Ordinances of God.</note> and they that were not ſeparated met together in the publique place of worſhip; Neither is it improbable but as they had many who ſtood firmely for this coeleſtiall bond unto their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, ſo they had ſome who gaineſayd it, withſtood it, and oppoſed it; yet you ſee that notwithſtanding all this they ſeparate from none but groſſe Idolaters; we muſt not for the ſins of our fellow worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, nor for difference of opinion amongſt our ſelvs make a ſeparation from the true church. Was not the Church in Chriſts time a perverſe Church? Math. 5.21.22. Math. 15.6.7.8. 1 Cor. 2.8.9. And did he not forbid to ſeparate from this Church, Mat. 10.6.7. Mat. 23.2.3. Did he not himſelf preach in their Temple. Joh. 8.2. And reaſon with them in his owne perſon about Religion? Ioh. 10.24.25.26. Surely Chriſts precept back with his owne preſident may be our warrant not to deſert our Congregations.</p>
            <p>When did the viſible Church in any age ſince <hi>Adam</hi> not conſiſt of a mixt multitude? ſhe hath bin, and doe what we can, ſhe will bee a Lilly amongſt the thornes. If I goe further I ſhall exceed a Paraphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique expoſition, I therefore refer you to <hi>Rutheford, Bernard, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:125569:12"/> Ball.</hi> But it may bee you now diſlike us becauſe of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and diſtractions amongſt us. I cannot deny our many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentings, one being amongſt us for <hi>Paul,</hi> another for <hi>Apollos,</hi> one for <hi>Cephas,</hi> another for Chriſt; nor yet our grievous and lamentable diſtractions, being ſprung from the civill jarrs of one faith. I confeſſe them with griefe, I wiſh I could remove them with prayers, or wipe them away with my teares. But becauſe the ſonnes of my mother jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle amongſt themſelves, and proceed from wrangling to fighting. I will not therefore deny her, run away from her, or deſert her. I know that her Childrens diſſention is her griefe, and ſhall I adde affliction to her ſorrow?</p>
            <q>From the people of the Lands.</q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note>WHat are they that are here meant by the people of the lands? </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>The Canaanites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Iebuſites the Ammonites, the Moabites, the Aegyptians and the Amorites, Ezr. 9.1.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note>How were they joyned to theſe Idolaters? </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>Contrary to Gods Command they were joyned unto them in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, neither was it the ſin of the vulger ſort alone, but the very hands of the Princes and Rulers were chiefe in this treſpaſſe, Ezra. 9.2.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who are not ſeparated enter not into the oath, and the curſe for the obſervation of Gods Statutes <hi>with their brethren the Nobles;</hi> their ſtrange Wives have with-drawne them, their Idolatrous conſorts have ſet them in oppoſition againſt this Covenant, which is likely to prove a ſtrong promover of Religion, in its purity, power, &amp; perfection.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> Matrimoniall League with Idolaters, a ſtrong barr to keep out the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</note>Marriage with ſtrangers, or matrimoniall leagues with Idolaters, are not onely an inlet unto falſe worſhip, but a ſtrong bar to keepe out the power of godlineſſe. This made <hi>Ezra</hi> when hee heard of it, rent his garment, plucke off his haire, and ſit downe aſtonied: Shall our eyes be dry? ſhall we not even for this bedew our cheekes with our teares? It is our ſin of England as well as it was the ſin of Iſrael, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others we eſpecially feele the ſmart of this now; wee muſt be deeply humbled, or elſe God will not be reconciled.</p>
            <q>And all they that had ſeparated, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> Covenanting Chriſtians ſhould bee couragious Chriſtians.</note>THeſe men now take heart of graſſe unto themſelves, they are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to continue no longer ſlaves to ſin, and bondſlaves unto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; they ſee their wickedneſſe is a let to their happineſſe, they now with violence breake through the thorne-hedge of corrupt deſires; they matter not for toyle, they prize their liberty, they value not their bloud, come what can come, they will ſound out the Trumpet, ſtrike up the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:125569:13"/> Drumme, and fight againſt their luſts which continually war againſt their ſoules; As good ſouldiers of Chriſt, ſo that Idolatry may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, other evills ſubdued, and that God may bee appeaſed, they care not what hardneſſe they undergoe; they are martiall men, and they have got mighty minds, as they have got courage for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, ſo they hope to obtain the conqueſt. They doe not now like milk-ſops, white-livered fellowes, or ſaint-hearted creatures for feare of blowes, deſert devotion, relinquiſh religion corrupt conſcience, pervert piety, depreſſe ſtrictneſſe, and ſuppreſſe ſincerity; they dare now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and as much as in them lyeth dignifie the honourable, and noble peereleſe Cauſe of Gods precious people, they matter not what dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger they put themſelves upon, ſo they can ruinate and repreſſe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent, wicked, and inſupportable abhominations of Belials baſe and helliſh brood. They are not apsaled and affrighted, like ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable and pufillanimous ſpirits, or as <hi>Salomons</hi> ſluggard with the Lyons in the way, they are determined to hazzard their lives to maintaine Chriſts cauſe, and to uphold the practicall profeſſion of Chriſtianity. O beloved, had they bin timorous, they had bin unfit for this military courſe, but it ſeemes they have ſpirit, for what doe they know but that this Covenant may ſet all the Heathens in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell array againſt them? their familiar acquaintance may be as <hi>Iudas,</hi> and their late Idolatrous wives may be as Dalilah to betray them; yet for all this they will not be diſmayed, they pluck up a good heart, paſſe through the Pikes, adventure upon difficulties, and rather then they will not covenant with God, put themſelves upon the perill of their lives. O that we like theſe had magnanimous and undaunted ſpirits, as we ſhould be content, to reſiſt to bloud, ſo we ſhould anſwer our cruell and bloudy oppoſers as that renowned <hi>Casſibelane</hi> the Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine anſwered <hi>Caeſar,</hi> I have not yet learned to live in ſervitude, but with weapons in hand to defend the liberty of my Country; wee are not yet contented to live in Romiſh or infernall ſlavery, we have learned to maintaine the rights and liberties of our Celeſtiall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, we feare not brandiſhed ſwords, menacing ſpeeches, no not the utmoſt that adverſe powers can doe unto us, we feare not perills, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Gods Cauſe ſhall lye bleeding upon the ground, we will adueuture the pouring out the warmeſt bloud that runs in our veines. Theſe expoſtulate not the caſe with carnall reaſon, as many doe in our daies, they doe not ſay, This Covenant tends to the utter ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of all will-worſhip whatſoever, no Idolatry, no not the leaſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:125569:13"/> muſt be countenanced if this take place, wee are ſure to loſe many friends, and to undergoe the threates of great mens frownes, a great part of our Eſtates are likely to bee exhauſted, and our very lives may come to be endangered. Will not thoſe who are averſe unto the Covenant, who have ſworne to uphold Babell, to ſide with the ſcarlet Whore, (and to defend the Anti-chriſtian cauſe) grow very furious, and become much more enraged againſt us, will they not by open force, and by all ſecret Stratagems ſeeke the ſpoyle and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing of us, they laſht us before with whips, but it is to bee feared they will be turned to Scorpions; we thought in times paſt that their hand was heavy, but now they will lay more loade, yea, cauſe their little fingers to be farre more ponderous than their fathers loynes; for ought we know, this may cauſe our diſ-affected wives privately in revenge to murder us, our ſervants (who by this are ſure to be abridged of their former liberty) to riſe up againſt us; but if theſe ſhould be quiet, yet <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> the King of Perſia, and other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces about us, whoſe religion we goe about to ſuppreſſe, may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably take up armes, and breake in violently upon us. It is good to prevent theſe dangers, it is ſafe ſleeping in a whole skin, the beſt courſe to remove theſe feares, and to take away theſe doubts is not to accept, but to reject this covenant. O beloved, ſuch thoughts as theſe doe not trouble their heads, theſe are not ſcar-crowes to keepe them from this holy league; indeed they had cauſe at this time (as much as any people under the cope of Heaven could have) to cogitate thus with themſelves, but ſuch is their zeale with their undaunted courage, that they looke beyond perils, come life, come death, with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent they will take the covenant,</p>
            <q>Their Wives.</q>
            <p>WOmen are the weaker veſſells,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> Women not priviledged from ſpirituall vowes.</note> but though weaker no more then men priviledged from ſpirituall vowes; as they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſin, ſo their ſoules are expoſed to danger as well as others; therefore it is requiſite that with others they ſhould make uſe of all meanes for ſinnes prevention: Covenants are corroſives to eate out dead fleſh, and the prime Antidote to prevent future diſtempers; Theſe men love their wives, they are loath they ſhould dye of their vitious Ulcers; like wiſe men, men of knowledge, they ſeeke out for remedy, they have taken advice, they are told, ingagements to God will daunt the courage of corruption, that ſelfe tyes for exact
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:125569:14"/> obſervance, will make ſinnes heart like <hi>Nabals,</hi> and cauſe it to give up the ghoſt; that ſelfe-ſearching, ſelfe-mourning, ſelfe-condemning, and ſelfe-covenanting, will eate out the core of iniquity, heale the conſcience, and preſerve the poore ſoule in ſafety; they are glad of their directions, they make haſte to their houſes, they cannot be quiet in their ſpirits, this counſell is as fire in their bones, they muſt needs forth-with relate it to their wives. But how is it taken with their conſorts, is it not too ſharpe, too biting, too full of vexation? No, they are ſo taken up with thoughts of their healing, that the tartneſſe of the medicine doeth not diſcourage them. From its application, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it cheerefully, they lay it on willingly, and they keepe it on care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; for as ſince their diſeaſe is the ſame with their Husbands, they with them apply the ſame plaiſter, entring into a curſe and an oath to ſerve the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> 2. Chriſtians ſhould be p li. titians.</note>He that lookes not to all Ports is not likely to keepe out an enemy, to fore-ſee evills, and to prevent dangers is a point of policy. Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſhould be Polititians, we muſt not onely abſtaine from all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of evill, but cut off all occaſions whereby corruptions may be uſhered into our ſoules. Theſe grave Seniors of Iſraell leave not their wives at liberty while they ſtand bound, Nightingales ſing ſweetly, they are affraid of ſeduction, they doe not truſt them that lye in their boſome,<note place="margin">Sicut mulier adjutrix, ita ſaepe inſilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix, et ſicut portus eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugium, ita et ſaepe naufragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um parit. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
               </note> they bring them to the Covenant, that ſo they may be as deepely engaged as themſelves. Who but <hi>Evah</hi> perſwaded <hi>Adam</hi> to rebell againſt God? He was deceived, not by Sathan, but by his ſecond ſelfe; not by the Serpent, but by his Spouſe; not by the Divell, but by a woman; not by a ſtranger, but by his wife. Did not <hi>Iobs</hi> wife tempt him to evill? <hi>Iob,</hi> 2.9. <hi>Salomons</hi> wives turne his heart from God. 1 King. 11.4. and <hi>Ahabs</hi> wife enticed him to worke wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe before the Lord? 1 King. 21.25. Women are not alwaies hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, they are ſometimes ſeducers; they are not alwaies as a ſafe har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to their Husbands, there is ſometimes ſhipwrack of faith in their embraces.<note place="margin">Mulieres peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula ſemper in auribus habent. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
               </note>. Beloved, doe not falſe feares like falſe fires often burne in many womens breaſts? they are very timorous, ſuſpitions make deepe impreſſions. And what doe they doe when they are jealous of an approaching evill? ſurely buzze their feares into their husbands heads; uſing all allurements to draw them to the fulfilling and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of their deſires; they ſing Syrens ſongs, they are very obſervant of their humours: but <hi>latet anguis in herba,</hi> there is ſome
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:125569:14"/> miſchiefe at hand. It is very likely a ſuppoſed evill of affliction muſt now be kept off by ſome reall evill of tranſgreſſion. I thinke for this I may appeale to the conſciences of many, who by the enticing words of their flattering wives have bin put upon thoſe waies, which have afterwards cauſed horrour to their ſoules. From theſe men we may learne wiſedome, we may feare back-ſliding; <hi>Hee that ſtandeth muſt take heed leſt he fall.</hi> Let us therefore hedgein our ſelves with a holy vow, but out of that fence let us not leave our wives,, leſt they being forth, get us out by wiles to ſin againſt God.</p>
            <q>Their Sonnes, their Daughters, and all that had knowledge, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>THeſe words include all inferiours in the Domeſtique Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> None exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from a ſacred Vow.</note> It is for <hi>Ioſuahs</hi> houſhold as well as himſelfe to ſerve the Lord, Ioſh. 24.15. It is common with youth to lay the reines looſe upon the neck of their luſts, to follow their owne devices, and to purſue the imaginations of their evill hearts, the head-ſtrong crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt have a curbe; ſurely an oath and a curſe are a ſtrong reine to hold in the head of ſin.</p>
            <p>It is not a perfect body that is defective in its members, I much miſtake me, if both Church and Common-wealth will not challenge ſonnes and daughters as part of their members; why then by way of exemption from covenant ſhould they be ſeparated from the body? <hi>Nehemiah</hi> doth not ſhut ſervants out of doores; here is no Porter to keepe the gate faſt bolted againſt them; for hee ſaith, <hi>all that had knowledge tooke the vow,</hi> and as the Iewes had ſervants, ſo I ſuppoſe their ſervants were capable of knowledge. Servants be ſtones in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Church, and props to uphold the Common-wealth, and is it not fit they ſhould be well cemented, and faſt tyed by a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation?</p>
            <q>They clave to their brethren, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>THey clave,</hi> viz. they approved, they did not diſlike, they were cheerefull, they did not murmure, they were willing, they did not hang backe, they were ſincere, they did not diſſemble, they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, they did not halt, they were ſubmiſſive, they did not rebell, they were conſtant they did not fly off. Particular facts commended in Scripture, are generall examples &amp; bind to imitation, when either the ſame thing is elſe-where commanded, or where the ground, drift, and equity of the thing is not covered with a cloud. Theſe men judge not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:125569:15"/> with a fleſhly, but with a ſpirituall eye; the carnall man perceives not the things that are of God. A Covenant, eſpecially ſuch a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant would ſeeme harſh to a naturall judgement. Their way is not the way of the world, the Prince of the aire workes not upon them for diſobedience; they ſee the beauties of holineſſe, even the riches of Heaven, which is Chriſt, the hope of glory to their ſoules. Sin like falſe wares deludes not their ſoules with its curious gloſſe, the ſpirit of whoredomes is not in them, they know the Lord, and frame their doings to turne unto their God: Had contumacy ſate as regent in their hearts, in following vanity, they would have become vaine, they had gone after the Heathen, whom the Lord had charged them they ſhould not doe like unto them; they would have hardened their neckes, and ſteeled their countenance againſt this covenant; had they lookt through Natures proſpective glaſſe, this would have ſeem'd a nicity, not neceſſary, they ſee not men like Trees, their eye-ſight is cleared, they now judge this courſe neceſſary for their ſoules.</p>
            <p>Surely Iſrael is in a happy condition; ſhe hath a multitude of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, and therefore ſafe; ſhe hearkeneth to counſell, and therefore wiſe; ſhe ſoares not aloft with fooliſh conceites, ſhe is not ſwolne with the tympany of Pride, ſhe is not lifted up in her ſelfe (<hi>Nabal-</hi>like) above the good counſell of other men, preſuming that ſhe is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough to take directions from her owne principles; neither is ſhe obdurate or melted like waxe, either too hard to receive, or too ſoft to retaine any impreſſion, like them who through anguiſh of ſpirit hearkened not to <hi>Moſes</hi> the Meſſenger of their deliverance; neither is ſhe uncapable of advice, through ſimplicity which is the daughter of ignorance, or through jealouſie which is an effect of feare; ſhe ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects not a circumvention by her Nobles, as being cloſe minded, and therefore ayming at their owne ends; neither is ſhe wilfull or heady, becauſe ſhe would not be thought unable to direct her ſelfe, to judge what is needfull, or to manage her ſpirituall affaires; ſhe hath an eare open, and an heart attentive to the directions of her Worthies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> Examples of Superiors ſtrong cords to draw others to godlineſſe.</note>Examples of ſuperiours are ſtrong cords to draw on others to good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Pious Nobles are good guides, their religious actions are good inducements unto holineſſe; ſometimes to multitudes of perſons they are leading, ſwaſible and prevailing preſidents: Though it be true as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>If the Rruler hearken to lyes, all his ſervants are wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,</hi> and though <hi>Ieroboams</hi> Idolatry became Iſraels ſinne, yet when
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:125569:15"/> 
               <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> reſolved in the audience of his people, that hee and his hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold would ſerve the Lord, the people replied, that Gods ſervice was with him the ſubject matter of their choyce. Ioſh. 24.15.21.22. So when <hi>Ioſiah</hi> made a covenant to walke after the Lord, to keep his Commandements, his teſtimonies, and his Statutes with all his heart, they that were preſent in Hieruſalem and Benjamin, cavilld not againſt the fact, tooke not pett and withdrew themſelves in diſcontent, they are of flexible tempers, a willing people in the day of aſſemblies, they maintaine, and ſtand to what their Ruler hath done. 2 Chro. 34 31.32. O how good were it for inferiours, that Superiours devoted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to holineſſe, they might then guide their feet in the way of peace, have lighted torches continually burning before them; O how much better would it be for perſons in place of Authority to practiſe godlineſſe in then owne perſons? by this meanes they ſhould never increaſe the guilt and entent of their perſonall ſins, by making them exemplary to others.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Application.</note>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> See the excellency of pious Nobles, and what a mercy it is to have religious Worthies: I will not ſay that theſe were all, <hi>Natu Nobilus,</hi> noble by deſcent; yet this I may ſay, that they were <hi>Nobiles quia virtute fulgentes,</hi> they were fulgent in vertue, eminent for piety, and very radiant, Gods Image ſhining clearely upon their ſoules; The more men reſemble the Deity, ſurely I conceive they are the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with the robes of Nobility, they are not men that are ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to their vices, but men that excell in vertues, that are of Heroicke ſpirits; Hee is an onely Peere of Heaven, who diſdaines to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by his baſe corruptions. Theſe Nobles are like morning ſtarres, they by their godly endeavours bring light to a world of Perſons, they are excellent for brightneſſe, and they communicate their graces, as deſirous of the good of others: They are nurſing Fathers; Labour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reformation and preſervation, are Symptomes of paternall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they are miniſters of good, and therefore it is not ſin, but ſanctity, not evill, but good, that by their practiſe they preach unto the people; They are Leaders, and therefore they goe before them, by a holy vow guiding them in the way to heaven: They are ordainers, therefore they prefix order to the multitude, and to keep them in order, they frame an Ordinance, and that Ordinance is a Covenant; they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervators, they take notice of, and give directions for what is to bee done, they are Governours, or rather skilfull Mariners, they ſit at the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:125569:16"/> helme in the height of the ſtorme, and to keep the ſhip of their ſoules from ſplitting againſt the rocks of Gods dreadfull juſtice, as a ſtrong Anchor they caſt out a vow, that if by any meanes the people may be kept alive and not dye in their ſins. O happy Iſrael, thy Nobles are the pledges of thy rule, they confirme and commend the truth and goodneſſe contained in thy precepts; they direct thee in particulars concurring with thy injunctions, though not expreſſed in them; they toll thee on in obedience, though not paſſive, yet active; thou mayſt well keep going, when ſuch as theſe goe before to direct thee; Lazy travellers will hold out with good company which beat the path be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them: Thy great perſonages are not ſo taken up with the perſon for a time put upon them, that either in ſpeech, looke, or carriage, they ſhew that they forget their naturall condition, as men, or their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall eſtate, as Chriſtian men; thy are counſellable by themſelves, they are not oblivious of thoſe duties that concerne their ſevered con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in reſpect of another world. What are they have bin, thou canſt not now ſay that they are Idolatrous, they ſet not up Idols, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Idolatry, they are not rebellious, and companions of theeves, they imbrace communion with Saints; they are not ignorant, they are wiſe as Rulers, and learned as Iudges of thy Nation; they doe not with <hi>Diotrephes</hi> who loved the preheminence, refuſe to countenance Gods Meſſengers, they doe not prate againſt Gods ſervants with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious words, they forbid not them that would entertaine them, neither doe they excommunicate them, or ſhut them out of the Church. Thou maiſt rejoice O Iſrael in theſe thy Worthies, their deportment ſhews, that they are thy beſt Counſellors, there is ſquareneſſe, not partiality or perverſneſſe in their actions, they are wiſe to preſerve thee, not crafty to inſnare thee, they are active, not for their owne advancement, but for thy advantage, they are couragious for thee, not fearefull or faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted to defend thee, they are religious, but not factious, ſecret, but not fraudulent, they are well read in thy preſent eſtate, and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of what may promote thy future felicity, and therefore as they have provided a ſolemne Covenant, ſo they as fellow-brethren joyne with thee in a ſacred Oath for ingagement unto God. See then in theſe thy happineſſe, they are not as croſſe winds to keep thee from ſhore, they are as proſperous gales to bring thee in ſafety to the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Bee glad thou daughter of Zion, and with ſhouting expreſſe thy rejoycing for theſe thy Nobles.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:125569:16"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> O yee Senators of the Land, let theſe Worthies bee your examples, parallel theſe in pious actions, then glory and renowne will bee as a Crowne and Diadem ſet upon your heads: It is reported of <hi>Ageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus,</hi> that in travelling hee alwaies tooke up his lodging in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to the intent that men and Gods might ſee into his actions; All things are naked to the eye of Heaven therefore in all your conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and untertakings, reflect upon Iehovahs preſence, conſult with God, and act for God. Paul complaines of many, who ſought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but not Chriſt, ſtaine not your proceedings with by-ends, let Gods glory be your higheſt aymes, there is no ſafety in ſelfe ſeeking, as this argues filthyneſſe of mind in nobleneſſe of birth, ſo it is mans debaſement before the Lord; To ingratiate and inrich your ſelves, let not the ſkie of Soveraignty be the onely object of your ſight, nor the ſundry revolutions of Princes affections, bee the ſole heaven of your contemplation, <hi>Non nobis nati ſumus,</hi> next unto God ſeeke the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good, weigh your intendments in the fruit, as well as the flower, conſider what they will be to others, aſwell as your ſelves, be not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts in your places, looke that your deſignes have a publique ſtamp, that in the ſucceſſe they prove not a diſgrace, but an honour to your names; you muſt be men of more than private ſpirits, the Kingdomes ſafety muſt be your care, the Goſpells advancement muſt bee your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, and the peoples proſperity is the thing you muſt ſtrive for; Let not your workes at any time be workes of iniquity; ſuffer not an act of violence to be in your hands, permit not your feet to run to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, or to make haſt to ſhed innocent bloud; why ſhould your thoughts be thoughts of perverſeneſſe? why ſhould waſting and deſtruction bee in any of your pathes? A friend is borne for the day of adverſity; wee doe not looke at you as having virgins faces, and vultures ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons, we take you not to be fained, but faithfull friends, wee are yet in diſtractions, ceaſe not to help us by your counſells, you have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtood for our liberty, ſtill ſtand as pillars of marble,<note place="margin">Quanto illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriores ſunt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines in ſaecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, ſcientia it genere, tante pluribus ſuit perditionis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplura <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>109</hi>
               </note> ſpare not your paines, ſpare not your bloud for the preſervation of our felicity; bee not as the children of Ethiopians before the Lord; O Let the light of your lives, aſwell as the light of your Counſells make it apparent that Iehovah judgeth amongſt the Gods; to adviſe well, and live ill, is to build with one hand, and pluck downe with an other; Scarlet Robes are ornaments to your bodyes, but ſcarlet ſins will prove the debaſement of your ſoules; it is the tranſparent chriſtall glaſſe of your
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:125569:17"/> holy life, that will ſhew us the ſpots upon our garments, and your ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloſe unto the Covenant for God, that is likely to conglutinate our affections more unto your ſelves, and as a leading preſident give us encouragement for a religious walking before the Lord. Thus qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, our ſubject ſhewes you, you ſhould be; and thus farre you ſee, the example of zealous Peeres prevaild in the daies of old.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Let us beloved of this Nation take Iſraels practiſe into imitation; they may well be reſembled unto ſtarres: Starres are lights, they ſhine as lights in the world, endeavouring to be blameleſſe and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, the ſonnes of God without rebuke in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe generation, Philip. 2.15. So ſoone as the Sunne appeares, and breakes out with its radiant beames, they vaile their owne glory. God can no ſooner declare himſelfe in the beauties of holineſſe, but theſe caſt the vaile of humble ſubmiſſion over their owne faces, and by obedience give him the honour due unto his Name. There is a pleaſing and a concordiall harmony amongſt the ſtarres, and theſe are not different in their deſires, nor diſſonant in their actions; ſtarres are coeleſtiall bodies, theſe are not now terrene in their affections, they are heavenly minded, they expreſſe their reſurrection to newneſſe of life by ſeeking the things that are above, ſpirituall righteouſneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, is that which they ſeeke for; Little ſtars doe not envy great ones, theſe are ſo farre from emulation, that they rejoyce in the zeale, and triumph in the forwardneſſe of their Nobles; Heathens oppoſe the truth of Gods Worſhip, ſeeking to cloud it with their owne fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and ſuperſtitious vanities; theſe as ſparkling and glorious ſtarres, breake out in a blacke and a darke night: As ſtarres are conſtant in their courſes, and keepe their appointed places; ſo theſe without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring, without negligence, adhere in covenant to theſe their religious Worthies. Laſtly, as ſtarres communicate their light to us, betwixt whom there is a great diſtance, ſo theſe Iſraelites to the remoteſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yea, to the ends of the world hold out a Preſident, for taking and keeping of a holy covenant. Selfe-love and over-weening con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceites doe not now as with wings carry them aloft, they are privy to their failings, apprehenſive of their miſery, and depreſſed in their thoughts, for making their Peeres their copy to write by, and their ſole example for imitation, they both acknowledge the want of, and declare their deſire after their perfection. <hi>Be you followers of me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to the Church of Corinth, <hi>as I am of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:125569:17"/> many thinke they are in a good condition if there be any worſe then themſelves, but theſe ſtrive not with the worſt, but with the beſt, making apace, as faſt as they can after them, though they come far behind them, both in their zeale and in their wiſedome; theſe men are not now aſleep as they were before, their conſciences are wakened, the eye of their underſtanding is opened, and they ſee in this their day the things that belong unto their peace: lately they were inſenſible of ſins deceit, and the ſpirituall death of their ſoules; now with the Apoſtle they feele the deſtructive power of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and cry out, <hi>O wretched men that wee are, who ſhall deliver us from this body of death!</hi> now they conceive a kind of neceſſity of Damnation, becauſe that cuſtome in ſin hath bred a neceſſity of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in them; now they conſider whither ſin, Satan, and their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous wives would carry them, now they lay to heart the juſtice of God ſtanding before them as an Angel with a drawne ſword ready to fall upon them, if they poſt on ſtill in the way of tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, therefore to preſerve them from utter ruine they begin to ſet themſelves in battaile array, they <hi>put on the ſhield of faith, the breaſt-plate of righteouſneſſe, and the helmet of ſalvation,</hi> that ſo they may forth-with wage war againſt their luſts; they doe not ſtand hove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the aire, as men not fully reſolved, ſaying, ſhall we, ſhall we? they are growne reſolute, though they paſſe through fields of iron, and ſtreames of bloud, they will ſet upon a ſtrict courſe, to curbe their heady corruptions, and that courſe you ſee is a covenant to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſtatutes of the Lord: theſe are not like many, to pretend much and performe little, they doe not breake off now it comes to the pinch, conſtancy crownes their purpoſes, and is as a wreath of Lawrell girding the temples of their ſacred reſolutions, for they fly not off, but <hi>cleave unto their brethren the Nobles.</hi> O that we for ſplendency could make them our patterne, O that in humility, we could follow them, and that in conſtancy we came not farre behind them; examples are ſometimes efficacious doctrines. <hi>Sozomen</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, that the devout life of a poore Captive Chriſtian woman, made a King and all his family imbrace the faith of Ieſus Chriſt; and <hi>Euſebius</hi> from <hi>Clement</hi> tells us, that when a wicked accuſer had brought Saint <hi>Iames</hi> to condemnation, ſeeing his Chriſtan for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, he was touched in conſcience, confeſſed himſelfe to be a Chriſtian, and ſo was taken to execution with him, where after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:125569:18"/> and forgiveneſſe, they kiſſed, and prayed for each other, and ſo were both beheaded together. Iſrael is no ill guide, at this time ſhee is a very good patterne, her light like a cleare and a bright Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amond, may well ſhine in the darkneſſe of our ſoules, her ſplendor may be the glorious object of our ſight, her preſent covenanting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction calls aloud to us for ſpeedy imitation, therefore let us up and be doing, let us take her vow upon ourſelves, and vowing adhere, and ſtick cloſe unto our noble Worthies.<note place="margin">Motives.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That we may not be ſlack to the worke, but ſetting theſe Iſraelites as a pillar of fire before us, walke after them in our adherence to our Nobles, let us conſider what they are in their ſeverall relations, and what they are declared to bee by their particular actions.</p>
            <p>They are Patriots, not Traytors to their Country; like homebred vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers they ſeek not to corrodate &amp; eat out their mothers bowels, they deſire not through the ſea of bloud to ſwim to the cape of their hope, they have vowed with theii lives to defend our Kingdomes liberties; they doe not ſay as <hi>Antonius Baſſianus Caracalla,</hi> ſometimes Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of Rome, ſaid <hi>(quod libet licet)</hi> the Law is the rule of their will, their will ſets not Confines to the Law, they doe not what may pleaſe themſelves, but what they may and muſt doe for the preſervation of this our Nation; they like <hi>Aelius Adrianus</hi> ſeek ſo to governe us, that it may be apparent that it is our wealth, not their owne that they ſeeke for.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They are zealous for God, not deſperate Rebels againſt God: They have formerly ſolemnely proteſted to maintaine and uphold the Proteſtant Religion againſt all Popery, and popiſh innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whatſoever, and they have now ſworne to defend Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip againſt Atheiſts, and armed Papiſts, who endeavour with their ſoule feet to bemuddy the waters of the Lords Sanctuary; to ſtand for Religion, I hope, is not to ſtand againſt God, to labour to uphold the Church in her purity, is not to oppoſe and perſecute Chriſt, becauſe theſe love the Lord, they ſeeke to ſet up his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and becauſe the loves of Chriſt are better than wine unto their ſpirits, they deſire that in England with a more Majeſtique and commanding power he may be ſet upon his Throne; They will not with <hi>Iulian</hi> apoſtatize from Chriſt, they will not with <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocleſian</hi> perſecute his Saints. Now God hath called them out to a perfect reformation, they will not have it ſayd of them as it was of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:125569:18"/> ſome, that the Nobles put not their necks to the worke of the Lord. Nehe. 3.5. They are not like ſome in our times, who care not to damne themſelves, that they may hurt the Church, they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſemble <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> they have no leſſe care of the Church of God, than they have of their owne ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> They are Loyall, not perfidious to our King; Have they not vowed to defend his Majeſties Royall perſon, Crowne, dignities, and eſtate? wherein have they dealt falſely, in what particular can you lay treachery to their charge? They love his ſoule, they will not corrupt it by ill counſels, they had rather fence it, (that ſin may not breake in upon it) by chriſtian advice: they know that ſin is the ſoules poyſon; It appeares by their prayers for him, they would not have ſoule-guilt laid to their charge, they would have our King hereafter as a bright morning ſtar to ſhine in the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; They love his Majeſties perſon, it is his preſence that they long for, not his abſence that they are content with; Stangers both in Nation and religion doe daily inviron him, they feare it may make for his ruine, and his good peoples deſtruction, they beſeech his Majeſty to withdraw himſelfe from them, they are confidently perſwaded of his ſweet and pliable diſpoſition, they ſtrive therefore to remove evill Counſellors from him, they ſo thirſt ofter the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him, that they are willing to hazard their lives to get him. His Majeſties peaceable returne unto them will bee the rejoycing of their hearts; they ſtand for his State, wealth, Honour, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, they are willing to ſettle, if not to increaſe his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue. and they have ingaged themſelves to make him as glorious as any of his Predeceſſors that have gone before him. Surely our King himſelfe believes, that ſuch of the Pilots Royall of this Land, as have made uſe of, and relyed upon the auncient Lawes, and long ſetled Cuſtomes of this Nation for their guard and compaſſe, for the guiding of the Barke of this Common-wealth, have moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably and proſperouſly ſayled through all the moſt dangerous and difficult paſſages, and rougheſt billowes, in the moſt boyſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſtormes, and at length have arrived at their deſired Haven, with infinite glory to themſelves and to the Nation, or elſe he would never have ſaid unto them; <hi>We doe engage unto you ſolemnely the word of a King, that the ſecurity of all and every one of you from violence, is, and ever ſhall be as much our care, as the preſervation
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:125569:19"/> of Vs and our Children.</hi> Thus you ſee his Majeſty judgeth them faithful, why ſhould we then thinke then diſloyall? He aſſures them of his adhering to them, and care of them, ſaying, <hi>Hee will be as carefull of his Parliament, and of the Priviledges thereof, as of his Life, and Crowne;</hi> And ſhall not wee encourage them, by promiſing to aſſiſt them, (ſo long as they ſtand for us, and for our Lawes) with out eſtates and lives? Seeing then they are thus, ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots for God, Fathers to the Country, and not rebellious, but loyall to his Majeſty; we need not feare to owne them, not ſcruple to be adviſed by them, not refuſe to enter into a holy Covenant with them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> They are not degenerate, they are truly generous, dangers doe not diſmay them, difficulties doe not diſhearten them, they have met with many ſtormes but yet they doe not hide their heads, they have had many diſcouragements, but yet they hold up their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, they have bin much toſt with waves, by reaſon of croſſe winds, but yet they are not hopeleſſe of getting to the harbour; The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell and the ſcarlet whore, with all the Romiſh faction have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined together againſt them, but yet they are not daunted, they ſtill contend for the Conqueſt, they yet play the men for the people and for the Cities of their God. Menaces from others, doe but breath a new life into their ſpirits; They know, that vertues com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion is not facility, the way that ſhee treads, muſt be rough and Thorny; They remember, that good things are hard to come by, the Goſpell and the Subjects liberty, are the Treaſures they ſearch for; they looke at theſe as worth their paines, as worth their labour, it is ſtill for theſe, that they adventure the loſſe of their precious lives. They are content for the preſent to beare that which diſpleaſeth them, that in the end (they may freely without interruption) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy theſe rich jewels, which if they get them, will prove advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous unto them and theirs; They are not ignorant, that quiet calmes are often ſubſequents to ſtormy tempeſts, and that ſowre accidents are ſometimes ſeaſoned with ſweet events, theſe, and ſuch like being the ſubject of their thoughts, they breake not off their intended purpoſes, they deſert not their preſident reſolutions, they alter not their propounded courſes, with a fixed countenance they out-ſtare the threatning eye of danger, they leave their vow as a witneſſe of their valour, they are determin'd to reſiſt to bloud, rather than
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:125569:19"/> forſake their God; life is not deare, it is the Lords ſtatutes that they covenant to keepe cloſe unto.<note place="margin">2 Chro. 19 2.</note> They that love God ſhould be the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of our love, it was <hi>Iehoſaphats</hi> ſin, that he helped the ungodly, and loved them that hated the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> They are a publike not a private or a cabinet counſell, they are the great and generall Counſell of the Kingdome; feare not that they will enſnare you, themſelves and their owne eſtates are inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, in all their decrees; they bid you doe nothing but what they have done themſelves, their covenant will not endanger you, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it prove perillous to withſtand Gods enemies, and to ſtand cloſe unto Gods Commands. A community is ſeldome prejudiciall unto it ſelfe or hurtfull unto others.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> They are our brethren. So they ſtiled the Scots in the act of paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and ſurely they will not deny us to be their brethren, who are of their owne Kingdome, and of their owne Religion; like brethren, in all their actions they deſire our welfare; they have bin ſtudious to contrive, and they are reſolute to performe, and this preſent covenant they have ſet forth for the publike good: like el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der brethren they command with love. Let us not hang backe, but joy in our obedience; our Nobles like the Primitive Chriſtians are well read in Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Doctrine, they have begun to ſoare to the higheſt pitch of affection, they are willing to lay downe their lives for the brethren; ſome already in the common Cauſe are gone to Heaven in a bloudy Chariot; others now are in continuall perills, not knowing how ſoone death may cut in ſunder the thred of their lives; they may well take up the ſymbole of <hi>Alphonſus Neopolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> viz, the Pelican drawing the bloud out of her breaſts for the feeding of her young, and conſidering for what it is that they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture themſelves, they may annex unto it this inſcription, <hi>Pro lege, pro grege.</hi> Shall they thus freely (for our Kingdomes Lawes, and for our ſafety) give up their ſelves, as it were in ſacrifice, and ſhall we forſake them? O no; let their God be our God, their Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell be our Goſpell; let not their bondage be our freedome, their death be our life; let us like brethren dye with them, &amp; dye for them in the maintenance of this covenant, for keeping off all the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Jehovah:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> They are not onely brethren, but they are Noble brethren, they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:125569:20"/> are in high place, they are in great authority; his Majeſty hath made them his Counſellors by his owne Writt you have made them Patriots of your Country by your own: choyſe: Remember what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubject to the higher powers,</hi> hee ſpeaks not in the ſingular, but in the plurall number; denoting that there is more powers then one. I ſuppoſe you cannot deny them this priviledge; they have a prelation above you, though they be your brethren, yet they are to you as theſe were to Iſrael, <hi>your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Nobles.</hi> Liſten to their edict, they require, that you ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for your ſins, and amend your lives, they are willing with you to take out the ſame leſſon, therefore with them make a firme cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to turne from the evill of your waies.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Laſtly, doe but compare the times paſt with the time preſent: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly you put on mourning as a garment &amp; were ever and anon rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to hide your ſelves, whileſt men of corrupt minds, corrupt concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the faith, were the ſole counſellors of eſtate, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.28. The wind is turned, the caſe is altered; your righteous, your religious Nobles are now in authority, and that they may the better appeare to be ſo to the eye of your ſoules, conſider a little the particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, what counſell they give to our Soveraigne, is it not like that of the Seniors of Iſraell, doe they not adviſe him, if he will be the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of this people to ſpeake good words unto them, that they may be his ſervants for ever? 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.7.</p>
            <p>Secondly, what is the charge they give unto the Iudges of the land? Is it not that they muſt take heed what they doe, becauſe they judge not for man but for the Lord; that they let the feare of God be upon them, with whom there is no iniquity, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts? 2 Cro. 19.6.7.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, what injunctions doe they lay upon the Miniſtery? Doe they not bid the Levites ſanctifie themſelves, <hi>Sanctifie the houſe of the Lord, and carry forth the filthineſſe out of the holy place,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 29, 5, 6.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, have they not formerly put you upon faſting, and ſtill continue your dayes of humiliation, that you may afflict your ſelves before your God, to ſeeke of him a right way; for you, your little ones, and all your ſubſtance, Ezra. 8.21. And have they not now framed a Covenant for them and for us, to ſeeke the Lord God of our fathers, with all our heart, and with all our ſoul. O then, having
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:125569:20"/> uch mercies by them, let us adjoyne our ſelves unto them: They tender us a covenant, it is for holy obſervance, their counſell is wholſome, their demand is equall, and their tender is lawfull, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have led the way, let us with <hi>Iudah</hi> rejoyce at the Oath, 2 Chr. 15.12, 13, 14, 15. &amp; every one with them ſubſcribe for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elfe, that he will keepe cloſe unto the Law of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Queſt. </note>Wherein muſt <hi>we cleave unto our Nobles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw,</note>Firſt in obeying them; this the Doctour of the Gentiles impoſeth as a duty upon us, when he bids us be ſubject to principalities and powers, to obey Magiſtrates, and to be ready to every good worke, Tit. 3.1. and for this thoſe Iewes are a faire preſident be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in hauing a reverent eſteeme of them, as they are the Lords Vicegerents, ſo they are ſtiled Gods, Exod. 22.28. and it is our duty to <hi>render honour to whom honour is due. Rom.</hi> 13.7.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in being faithfull to them, we have ingaged our ſelves by ſolemne proteſtation to maintaine and defend them. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not maintaine the priviledges of Parliament, and deſtroy the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliament. Let us be loyall not perfidious, let us have no hand in any thing that may hurt them, if we know of any plot or projects againſt them, let us quickly and timely diſcover them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, in praying for them. <hi>Pray for Kings, and all that bee in authority</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 Tim. 2.2. <hi>Preces &amp; lachrymae ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma eccleſiae,</hi> your prayers may keepe off their enemies, ſtrong cries, and earneſt entreaties may be prevalent for your Nobles ſafeties. Conſider:</p>
            <p>Firſt, that your Worthies as they are now aſſembled are the foundation, and <hi>Baſis</hi> of government, and conſequently of the peace and happineſſe of the Kingdome: for as they create Law, by which we are governed in peace and quietneſſe, ſo they uphold the power and authority of the Law; ſo that if through the neglect of prayer you ſuffer the foundation to decay, the maine building can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not long ſtand. <hi>For where no counſell is, the people fall, but in the multitude of counſellors there is ſafety, Pro.</hi> 11.14.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that they are to you as <hi>Gideon</hi> and the Judges were to Iſraell, <hi>A hedge to keepe you within your bounds, and a ſtrong tower to keepe off the maine body of your ſinnes,</hi> Judg. 2.19.—8.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:125569:21"/> 33. Breake downe your hedge, you may ramble whither you pleaſe, demoliſh your Fortreſſe, and you lye open to the batteryes of all corruptions whatſoever; their dying may prove Idolatries Vivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, their death is likely to be the life of mens luſts, they may then goe a whoring after their owne inventions, therefore as you deſire the death of your ſins, pray for the life of your Nobles.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, how comes it to paſſe that hitherto notwithſtanding the malice of your bloudy adverſaries, your Goſpell hath had free paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and your Lawes have bin in force, Remember, that <hi>all the dayes of Samuel, the hand of the Lord was againſt the Philiſtines,</hi> 1 Sam. 7.13. you had need pray for them if they be once remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, your enemies will breake in, and if they prevaile, where is your life, nay, the life of your life, your law and religion?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the Heathens abhor'd ingratitude, wee profeſſe our ſelves to be Chriſtians, our prayers are our thankes, they expect that; and well may they looke for it in reſpect of their unwearied paines. Indeed when we call to minde what they have done for us, and ſuffered in our behalves, our lives ſhould not be deare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us for their ſakes, but I ſcarce beleeve that they will afford them their lives, who ſeldome or never vouchſafe them their prayers. O in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull wretches, let not ſuch unthankefulneſſe be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our Engliſh ſpirits.</p>
            <q>They clave to their brethren, &amp;c,</q>
            <p>THey were brethren, <hi>quoad carnens,</hi> as having reference to the fleſh, they all deſcended from the loynes of <hi>Abraham, Ioh.</hi> 8.39. They were brethren, <hi>quoad fidem,</hi> they all laid claime to the Promiſe, and they which are of faith, <hi>the ſame are the children of Abraham. Galat.</hi> 3.7. They are brethren in reſpect of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Brotherly love continues amongſt them, for now like brethren they ſeeke to doe them good. Laſtly, they are brethren, in reſpect of their mutuall conjunction in this entire covenant; and thus like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> they are not brethren in evill, cruelty is not in their habitations, the accompliſhment of wicked deſignes is not the ſubject matter of their deſires, to encourage themſelves in the way of iniquity, and to ſtrengthen their hands in the ſupport of Idolatry is out of their thoughts, the amending of their waies runnes in their minds, mutuall corroboration in the practice of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:125569:21"/> is the cauſe of their league, and ſtrictneſſe with ſincerity in the Lords ſervice, is the end of their preſent reſolves.</p>
            <p>Generally from this appellation, whereby they are called,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> 1 Pride becomes not noble ſpirits.</note> and with which, for ought that we know, they were well contented, you may obſerve, that pride becomes not noble ſpirits, Rulers muſt not be of inſulting natures; it is not an haughty carriage that addes to their praiſe, their chiefeſt ornament is an humble deportment: they are but wormes, why ſhould they ſwell? Did not Majeſty empty it ſelfe, when Chriſt was contented to become a ſervant? They are but Miniſters; and in their chiefeſt eminence, but Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters for good; why doe they not then condeſcend to men of low degree? Rom. 12.16. Thoughts of dignity muſt be laid downe, they muſt be refuſed where God may bee honoured. <hi>My heart is towards the Governours that offered themſelves willingly among the people: bleſſe yee the Lord, Iudg.</hi> 5.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In that thus freely, thus lovingly they cloſe with their motion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> 2. Infer our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from their Nobles, as motions from affectionate Brothers.</note> eyeing them in this affable and familiar relation, collect thus much for your inſtruction: That Subjects muſt accept of motions from their Nobles, as motions from affectionate brothers.</p>
            <p>What is the reaſon our late Ordinances are not obſerved: that their injunctions are not obeyed, and that their Covenant is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſtrange, being but a bit to hold in the head of their luſts? I feare me it is becauſe our Nobles themſelves are ſtrangers not brothers in our repute. But leaving them wee will caſt our eye upon the Vow or Covenant it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And they entred into a curſe, and into an Oath, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To curſe, is to wiſh, and pray for evill things, and execrable to befall others, or our ſelves; When <hi>David</hi> was charged with affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the Kingdome, and ſeeking <hi>Saul</hi> his depoſition, if not his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, for his owne clearing, he makes uſe of dreadfull a impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſaying; <hi>If I have done this, let the Enemy perſecute my ſoul, let him tread down my life upon the earth, and lay mine honour in the duſt.</hi> Pſal. 7.3.4.5. His ſoule by a Synechdoche ſets out his perſon, his life the exiſtence of his perſon amongſt the living, and his honour, his dignity &amp; glory in this world, and in the world to come. It is grievous perſonally to be oppreſſed, more grievous to have the light of life extinguiſhed, but moſt grievous with the depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:125569:22"/> of life, inſtead of glory, to have perpetuall ignominy laid upon him, yet all this in caſe he be guilty, he is content with, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to cleare his innocency, he calls for no leſſe than this upon himſelfe. And this did <hi>Iob, Iob</hi> 31.5.6.7 8. &amp;c. Neither was <hi>Paul</hi> the Doctor of the Gentiles ſhie of an Execration, when he called God for a Record upon his ſoule, that he came not to ſpare them at Corinth. 2 Cor. 1.23. In like manner theſe Iewes (in caſe they willingly or willfully breake the Law) give up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto the curſe. As if they ſhould have ſaid, Lord let evill befall us, miſerie overtake us, and ſorrow be the Lot of our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; Let calamitie be our portion, diſtreſſe our reward, and death and damnation it ſelfe the recompence of our ſoules, if wee againe returne to the Heathens, if for the future we be not obſervant of thy ſacred Statutes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> precation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d execrations be not uſuall, yet ſometim s they are very lawful <hi>Cautions.</hi>
               </note>Though imprecations and execrations be not uſuall, yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they are uery lawfull; they are not inhibited, by the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Saints, you ſee they are highly commended. This our Worthies were not ignorant of, as appeares by the cloſure of their late Covenant, wherein they call God to witneſſe the ſincerity of their intentions, for which they are content to anſwer at the Great day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall bee diſcloſed. Indeede I confeſſe theſe are not commonly in our ordinary affaires, nor raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but conſiderately to be uſed by any, and therefore uſe them but when other wayes the truth cannot be credited; but when by other meanes thy integrity cannot bee cleared, but that thy inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for Piety may be freed from the aſperſion of levity, and but as theſe Iſraelites did to bind thy ſoule hand and foot, that it ſtir not, that it ſtart not, from an holy walking before the Lord.</p>
            <q>And into an oath.</q>
            <p>THere bee three waies to confirme the truth; Affirmation, Aſſertion, and an Oath. In the firſt we onely ſay, yea, or nay; and whatſoever is above this, viz. (in our ordinary communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) is not good, but evill, Matth. 5.37. In the ſecond, when our word is lookt at as reprobate ſilver, and not taken for currant coyne, (the matter being weighty) we pawne our truth as one of our beſt jewells in an aſſeveration, and in this way ſometimes by a double Amen, did Chriſt ratifie his ſayings. In the third, when men will
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:125569:22"/> not accept of our owne pledge, we procure God for our ſurety, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whoſe juſtice in our Oath we enter into Counter-bond for pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment by him, if we goe about to deceive. And thus the Jewes to teſtifie the uprightneſſe of their hearts in the preſent Covenant, enter into an Oath with their Peeres.</p>
            <p>To ſweare, or to take an oath,<note place="margin">What an Oath is.</note> is a very ſolemne and religious calling of God to witneſſe, acknowledging that as he is the onely wiſe God, knowing the ſecrets of our ſoules, and the moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Patron, and faithfull defender of all Truth, ſo on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that he is a moſt ſevere Judge, and revenger of all ſuch as ſhall abuſe his Name, to witneſſe a falſe matter: or more briefly you may thus define it. An Oath is an holy invocation of God (as the beſt witneſſe of all truth) and the puniſher of all ſuch as prophane his Name in calling him to teſtifie an untruth. Thus in ſwearing God is made both <hi>Index</hi> and <hi>Vindex,</hi> for therein we deſire him, as the ſearcher of hearts, and Patronizer onely of truth, to evidence with us that we deceive not, and withall to take vengeance on us if we doe deceive. Oathes are two-fold, Aſſertory and Promiſſory,<note place="margin">Oaths are two fold.</note> Iſraell is ſure ſhe diſlikes her ſins, ſhe is not a ſtranger to her hearts riſing againſt her corruptions, ſhe knowes that her ſoule is grieved for her former tranſgreſſions, this ſhe affirmes by her preſent ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring before the Lord of Heaven: She ſees how ſhe hath deviated, ſhe purpoſeth a ſpeedy returne; ſhe is privy to her precedent rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, now ſhe vowes though a ſudden, yet a true not a fained refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: ſhe is conſcious that ſhe hath provoked the eyes of his glory, ſhe now promiſeth not againe to offend, but in every duty to pleaſe his Majeſty, and in all her endeavours to promote his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. And becauſe ſhe would not be fickle, but keepe faſt bound to her word, ſhe enters into a ſerious and a ſolemn oath.</p>
            <p>She ſweares in truth, for now ſeeing her ſelfe in the glaſſe of the Law, ſhe beholds her ſinnes as ſo many ſpots; neither is her purpoſe meerely formall, but reall for cleanſing, nor her intention hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall but ſincere, for the removall of the evill of her doings from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord: ſo that her oath is not devoyd of truth. Secondly, ſhe conſiders what ſhe binds her ſelfe from, viz. her former Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and what ſhe engageth her ſelfe unto, viz. to walke in ſpirit and truth in the preſence of Jehovah, ſo that ſhe ſweares in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:125569:23"/> Thirdly, her oath is in righteouſneſſe, for as ſhe ſweares to pleaſe God, ſo that ſhe may pleaſe him ſhe ſweares onely obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his commands.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> Wee may vow againſt Sin, we may ſwear obedience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.</note>Wee may vow againſt ſinne, we may ſweare obedience unto God. I thinke <hi>Saul</hi> did not ill in ſwearing that <hi>David</hi> ſhould not be ſlaine, when <hi>Ionathan</hi> asked him, <hi>VVherefore he would ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt innocent bloud, to kill him without a cauſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.56. neither did <hi>Iob</hi> offend proteſting his innocency, and atteſting his ſincerity by a ſolemne oath. <hi>As God liveth who hath taken away my judgement, and the Almighty who hath vexed my ſoule; all the while my breath is in me, and the Spirit of God is in my noſtrills, my lips ſhall not ſpeake wickedneſſe, nor my tongue utter deceit, Iob,</hi> 27.2, 3, 4. Thus did <hi>Aſa</hi> with his people, 2 Chro. 15.14, And this is the preſent act of theſe Iſraelites with their Nobles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Propheſying of the converſion of the Gentiles ſaith, <hi>That they ſhall ſweare by the God of truth, Iſai.</hi> 65.16. What are we but Gentiles? nay, doe we not profeſſe our ſelves to be converted Gentiles? Why doe we then ſtill ſit in ſinne by conſent, lye in it by working it, and by continuall cuſtome ſleepe in it, as upon a bed of Downe? Let us now awake, and ſtand up from the dead; let it be ſeene, that our eyes are in our head to fore-ſee ſinnes mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and to hide our ſelves; that our heart is at our right hand, to withſtand temptation: and with violent blowes to keepe off inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating and enſnaring corruption; and that we are not raſh in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of vowes. Let it appeare, that deliberateneſſe hath curb'd raſhneſſe, by a ſolemne oath againſt the evill of our wayes; And to this end conſider:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reaſons</note>Firſt, that naturally ſince the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> the Port-all of thy heart is very weake; Sathan ever and anon makes it his inrode to infect thy ſpirit: it ſtands in need of a ſtrong bar. A ſtrict oath for ought I know, is one of the beſt barrs wherewith thou maiſt bolt him out.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An oath wil penetrate and make a deeper impreſſion than a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe upon thy ſoul: It wil be as a ſpur continually in thy ſides, to put thee on to act that whereunto thou haſt engaged thy ſelfe. After the children of Iſrael had ſworne to come up to the Lord in Mizpeh, and that whatſoever he was that did not vouchſafe his preſence, ſhould
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:125569:23"/> be put to death. When they were aſſembled, the thoughts of their oath put them upon diligent inqueſt after the perſons that had ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented themſelves, they muſt needs for their oath ſake looke ſtrictly to them, and therefore they cry out, <hi>Who is there among all the Tribes of Iſraell, that came not up with the congregation unto the Lord? &amp;c.</hi> Judg. 21.5. And when the Benjamites; after they had vowed againſt them, lay ſtill as a bait before them: for being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, they were a daily object of their eye, yet their oath kept them to their precedent promiſe made unto the Lord; though they dwelt with them, yet they would not marry their daughters unto them. And therefore as to accuſe themſelves, ſo to ſhew that oathes make an impreſſe upon the conſcience, with one voyce they give out this expreſſion, <hi>Though there muſt be an inheritance for them, that be eſcaped of Benjamin, that a Tribe bee not deſtroyed out of Iſraell, yet we may not give them wives of our daughters, for we have ſworne the contrary,</hi> Iudg. 21.17.18. Promiſes for the moſt part with ſome are but as morning dewes; when as a ſolemne oath is as a great raine that ſinkes downe, and is long ſeene upon the earth; they are many times not ſo ſoone ſpoken, but ſo ſoone forgotten: when oathes ring in the eares, and will be obſerved, preſſe upon the ſoule and will not be kept out. What is the reaſon that after ſo many vowes to God, not onely in the dayes of diſtreſſe, but upon the receipt of mercies, you have againe corrupted your ſelves with your owne devices? ſurely had you ſworne as well as promiſed, you would not like broken bowes have ſtarted from the Lord. <hi>Sauls</hi> ſubjects being ſworne not to eate untill the evening, though the Hony dropt, they durſt not put their hands to their mouthes for feare of the oath, 1 Sam. 14.26. As there is glory, ſo there is dread in the rayes of Majeſty, a remiſſe, and a careleſſe creature will remember himſelfe what he ſhould doe in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his Prince. God hath ſtampt a Majeſty and power upon a ſolemne oath.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note>But what ſhall I doe, that ſwearing I may ſweare aright, both for God, and againſt my ſins?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>Firſt, be ſure that ſin and thy affections be at a diſtance, that the league that was formerly betwixt them, is quite broken, that the loues of Chriſt are better than wine to the taſte of thy ſoul, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:125569:24"/> that becauſe that thy heart is united to the God of Heaven, that therefore thou art afraid to offend him. For he that ſweares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin, and yet doth not deteſt, but love ſin, and ſweares obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto God, and hath not a ſpirituall panting and braying after God, doth not deale fairely, hee hath two faces under one hood, he doth but diſſemble with the Lord, he ſweares not truly, that feares not God unfainedly: Deut. 6.13. <hi>Paul</hi> is certaine that he ſerves God in the ſpirit, before he call him to witneſſe his actions. Rom. 1.9.</p>
            <p>Secondly, doe this deliberately, conſidering ſins ſinfullneſſe, and ſtrictly viewing the beauties of holineſſe; inconſiderate vowes are ſoone broken, therefore be not raſh with thy mouth, and let not thy heart be haſty to utter any thing before God. Eccleſ. 5.2.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, looke at thy call to thy oath, a good call is a good warrant, we muſt not be Knights of the Poſt: By frequency and forwardneſſe, we muſt not give out ſuſpition that wee are prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall of our owne credit, and of our owne ſalvation. Prophane wretches often rap out oathes againſt their ſins, and yet doe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what they have done, and what they ſhould doe, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with double both their ſins and their Oathes. If Iſraels Nobles firſt ordaine it, take it, and ſubſcribe it, ſhe hath then good ground to accept it; we have a faire call, our Worthies are gone before us, let their Preſident be our encouragement, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it to us, and require the taking of it at our hands; we ſhall reſiſt authority in their publique call, if we take not the Oath againſt our ſins.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gratum eſt, deo q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um videt non ſponte donuo confirmare vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis noſtris que ante &amp;c. <hi>2 Chro. 15.15</hi>
               </note>Fourthly, doe it cheerefully, not unwillingly, doe it freely, in taking it, expreſſe alacrity; Forced ſervice is not pleaſing ſervice; conſtrained obedience neither with God nor man receives ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance: It is ſaid of Iudah, that they all rejoyced at this oath; could we doe thus, and ſweare with all our hearts againſt our luſts, ſeeking the Lord with our whole deſires; we ſhould have more hope than wee yet have, that God would bee found of us, and that in ſtead of our feares and preſent diſtractions, in reſpect of our bloudy warres, he would give us reſt round about us.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, if thou doe it, doe it without any reſervation, take it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt every ſin, and by it bind thy ſelfe to all the duties of Pietie
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:125569:24"/> whatſoever; one dead flie ſpoiles the whole oyntment; one ſin reſerved, one duty left out, and ſecretly excepted by thee, will make thee guilty of perjury before the Lord. For tell me, I appeal to thy conſcience, canſt thou ſwearing to keep all Gods Statutes willingly commit the leaſt ſin, or with ſelfe allowance omitt any duties, and not falſifie thy oath?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, be not onely reſolved of the Lawfulneſſe of it, in reſpect of the authority that impoſeth it, and the ſubject matter of the ſame, neither be thou onely perſwaded of its neceſſity, as it is a heavy weight to depreſſe thy corruptions, and as it is a ſtrong bar to keep in thy ſoule from ſtragling <hi>Dinah</hi>-like in the way of tranſgreſſion, but in taking it avoyd wavering, for as whatſoever is not of faith is ſin; So a wavering minded man is unſtable in all his wayes, I op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe wavering to conſtancie, be thou reſolute ever to keep it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve peremptorily with thy ſelfe, never to be found guilty of the breach thereof; Thus doe theſe Nobles, thus doe theſe Iſraelites, and thus obſerving theſe rules in thy oath for God, and againſt thy ſins; thou ſhalt ſweare in verity, not falſely; in judgment, not raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in righteouſnes, and not wickedly.</p>
            <q>To walke in Gods Law.</q>
            <p>THeir own fancies ſhal not now be the rule of their actions,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> Gods Statutes the Chriſtians way.</note> the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh practiſes of wicked Idolaters ſhall not now be the helm with which they will ſteere the courſe of their lives, their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſhall be ſuch as will endure the touchſtone, it is to the Law, and to the Teſtimony that they goe for direction. And no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, for a conſcionable walking according to Gods will and exact obſervance of his ſacred Statutes, is the chriſtians way, the Saints path, and the onely high road that leades to eternall life; I have gone aſtray ſaith <hi>David</hi> like a loſt ſheep, ſeeke thy ſervant, for I do not forget thy Commandements, Pſal. 110.176. <hi>Peccare, eſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viare,</hi> whilſt men ſin, they ſtraggle, whilſt they yield unto their vile affections, they deviate from the Lords Statutes.</p>
            <q>VVhich was given.</q>
            <p>That which was given, is ſtill continued; for as there is a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo there is a conſtancy in all Gods mercies; God is not as man that he ſhould repent; the gifts and calling of God are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance. It was mercy, not merit that brought her the Law. the cauſe moving was in the beſtower, not the receiver, ſhe was as
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:125569:25"/> well as others in the bloud of her ſins; ſhe before God caſt an eye of pitty upon her,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> The Law an effect of Gods love.</note> unwaſhed, unbathed, unſwadled as well as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. The Law, and the continuance of the Law is an effect of Gods love. Becauſe he affected her, he choſe her from amongſt the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and further to teſtifie his love to her, hee pluckt up the floud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, and let forth the ſtreames of the Law unto her, that ſo ſhee might cleanſe her ſelfe from all uncleanenes whatſoever. <hi>He ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his World unto Iacob, his ſtatutes and his judgements unto Iſrael; he hath not dealt ſo with any nation, and as for his judgements they have not knowne them, Pſal.</hi> 147.19, 20.</p>
            <q>By Moſes the ſervant, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>This title is as a glittering Diamond upon <hi>Moſes</hi> breaſt, it is not ſo baſe a thing as the world accounts it, to bee the Lords ſervant; Gods ſervice is the Chriſtians honour, not his diſgrace. The Jewes doe not thus ſtile him in any diſparagement, their thus calling him tends wholly to his praiſe. <hi>Socrates</hi> reports of <hi>Conſtantinus, Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinianus,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> three renowned Emperours in their times, that they called themſelves, <hi>Vaſſallos Chriſti,</hi> the vaſſals of Jeſus Chriſt. Looke at it therefore as one of the faireſt flowers in thy garden, that God hath entertained thee into his worke; glory not in thy wealth, thy friends, thy preferments; that man onely hath the Crowne, and the cauſe of daily rejoycing, that can ſay unto God, Lord, I am thy ſervant. <hi>Deo ſervire, regnare eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>To obſerve and doe all, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>GOds revealed Will is here ſet forth by foure ſeverall termes, Law, Commandements, Judgements, Statutes; it is a Law, for it hath a legiſlative power to bind over the ſoule to exact obedience: none may plead <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> all are bound to looke that they have the knowledge of the ſame. It is a command, we are intruſted with it, faithfully to obſerve it; it is a ſtatute, for as it is preſcribed and appointed, ſo it containes the whole duties of our lives; It is a judgement, for as there is involved in it the judgement, and judiciall ſentence of Almighty God, concerning its equity for our obſervance, ſo it will judge us at the laſt day, in caſe of contempt and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. As it is a Law it is worthy to be read, as it is a Command, it is not to be ſlighted; as it is a ſtatute it muſt be the rule of our life. And as it is a judgement we may ſee what it thinkes of our waies,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:125569:25"/> and what ſhall be our cenſure for the breach thereof. There is none of all this but Iſrael ſeemes to take notice of, and to witneſſe the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of her reſpect ſhe vowes and promiſeth obedience unto all.</p>
            <p>Chriſtians muſt not be their owne Carvers, they muſt not picke and chuſe, they muſt not take what they pleaſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> Gur obedience muſt bee uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall.</note> and leave what they liſt in the worke of the Lord; they muſt yeeld obedience, and ſhew a like tender reſpect unto the all Commandements of Jehovah. Was not this the lecture which <hi>Moſes</hi> read unto his people, when he told them, <hi>If they looke to love and prolong their dayes in Canaan, they muſt walke in all the waies that God had commanded them. Deut.</hi> 5.33. As this was the phraſe of <hi>Zachery,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth, Luk.</hi> 1.6. So it was <hi>Davids</hi> practiſe, who ſaid, <hi>he would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect not to one but all. Pſal.</hi> 119.6.115.128. the Prophet knew that there was the ſame equity in one that there was in anther, and in all that there was in ſome. I preſſe not legall but Evangelicall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, thou canſt not be free from ſin in every kind and degree thereof, onely without hypocriſie in the uprightneſſe of thy heart en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to frame thy ſelf to the whole Will of thy God. Thus doing, thy imperfect doing ſhal be accounted perfection. And if thou wilt be like Iſrael in doing all, then doe all ſpeedily, Pſal. 119.60. make fas;t, procraſtinate not the time, as delayes for cure ſo delayes for duty are dangerous. 2. Doe all cheerefully, Pſal. 27.8. Iſa, 2.23.55.5. A cheerefull ſervant beſt pleaſeth his Maſter. 3. Do all, but diſſemble not, ſeeke Gods glory in all. A faire glaſſe may be ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon falſe wares, God cannot abide a faire face and a falſe heart. Laſtly, doe all, but doe all conſtantly, be not found guilty of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy. If thou hold not out to the end aſſure thy ſelfe thou viſit loſe the crowne, Apoc. 2.10.11,</p>
            <q>And they entred into a curſe and an oath to walke &amp;c.</q>
            <p>WEE have viewed the words in their particulars, let us now caſt our eye upon the general, and therein upon the act that is performed by them; It is a Covenant, or a holy vow unto the Lord; which is no other than a binding themſelves to God, to doe ſome lawfull thing which is in his power, that he may the better attaine to his ſuits; This was a ſolemne cuſtome among the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, wherein the care of thoſe that were faithfull, was firſt to vow nothing but what was requiſite and requited. Num. 21.2. Iohn.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:125569:26"/> 24.25. Secondly, to ſee that the vowes that were made, were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly performed. Pſal. 22.25. Thus to doe is apprehended as a penſion of their duty, as a badge, nay as a Seale of a thankeful heart, and therefore walking to heaven in their deſires &amp; living with their head in their moſt ardent affections, they give up themſelves, they vow their ſervice, &amp; promiſe adherence to Almighty God; they find that by their former ſins God is provoked, they are willing to take any courſe whereby hee may bee appeaſed; they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they are much prone to wickedneſſe; they would ſet a Tutoror over their wills to keep them within the bounds of promiſed obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance; they may know experimentally, what are the fruits of hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full impiety; thraldome hath bin the fruit of their ſin, they would gladly have their bands broken, be wholy let looſe from captivity, and enjoy their freedome; they now conceive that God may be reconciled, they know no other but that he may be gracious, ſo that being grieved for ſin, groaning under preſſures, and hoping for deliverance, they now breake off their luſts, renounce their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries, and give up their ſoules and bodies in ſpirituall ſacrifice. From whence obſerve.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſervat.</hi> Sence of miſery under ſin and ſorrow. &amp;c. <hi>Proued.</hi>
               </note>That ſence of miſecy under ſin and ſorrow with hope of mercy, puts the ſoule upon covenants, yea ſure covenants for ſincere and exact obedience to the God of Heaven. Sins wounds are full of anguiſh, their ſmart, their paine is very dolourous; Nothing but Gileads balme can take out the fire, allay the heat, and mitigate the violence; Iſraels experience of this anguiſh ſent her unto God for cure; when renouncing her ſins, ſhee cried out, wee returne unto thee for thou art the Lord our God. Ierem. 3.22. When ſhee ſaw that iniquity had brought a diſtraction, and that ſuch was her diſtraction, that there was not peace to him that went out, nor to him that came in, but great vexations upon all the inhabitants of the Countryes, that Nation was deſtroyed of Nation, City of City, and that God did vex them with all adverſity, then to gett rid of her troubles, finding no other way left to procure her liberty, ſhe entred into a covenant to ſeek the Lord God of her Fathers with all her heart, and with all her ſoule. 2 Chro. 15.5.6.12. Sore laſhing makes a ſtubborne boy promiſe amendment, chaines and fetters brought <hi>Manaſſes</hi> to his knees, and theſe were <hi>Davids</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:125569:26"/> Pedagogue to teach him to know Gods Statutes. 3 When they were in bondage at Babilon, did not hope of Redemption, make them willing to take a tart medicine, they doe not ſing the dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ditty of accurſed <hi>Cain,</hi> hope as a Cordiall ſupported their fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſpirits, and as an anchor kept up their ſoules from ſplitting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rockes; though they goe weeping with their faces towards Zion, yet becauſe they hope their thraldome ſhall come to an end, and that their deſired liberty ſhall be accompliſhed, they will goe and try what they can doe by a ſolemne vow to aſſwage the wrath of their incenſed God. Iere. 50, 4.5. Hope well, and have well; but for hope the heart would breake.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Theſe Iewes in the Text ſee their ſins, they doe not conceale them, they are ſet downe in great Characters by them, that he that runneth may read them, they acknowledge their obſtinacy, having hardned their necks,<note place="margin">Peccati mario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne conſcientium illorum vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravit. et exper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve ſecit Deur. Regertuntur ad cor, et pecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum memoria pulſaat animus.</note> and appointed a Captain to return to their bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, Nehe. 9.17. Their Idolatry, having made them Idols, ſaying unto them, theſe are thy Gods. Nehem. 9.18. Their cruelty; having ſlaine the Prophets which teſtified againſt them to God. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem. 9.26. Their ingratitude, hauing done evill after the receipt of favours. Nehem. 9.28. And their pollution in all degrees, their Kings, their Princes, their Prieſts, having with them forſaken the Law, and not hearkened to Gods Commands. Nehem. 9, 33.34.35. Theſe ſins in their ſinfulnes, are now preſented to the eye of their ſoules, they are patient to God, impatient to themſelves, they ſmite upon their thighes, they are full of wrath, and reſolve againſt their luſts. Iob 34.31.32.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They are not inſenſible of miſery, they have not yet quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got the ſmart of the eye, the weales are not yet open, the ſtripes have not quite left bleeding upon their backes,<note place="margin">Non ceciduotur ex ſomno pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti exitantur.</note> they are ſcarce got out of thraldome from barbarous and cruell enemies, Neh. 9.36.37. they are loath to come againe into the ſame condition, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine therefore to leave their ſins for its prevention.</p>
            <p n="3">3 They are in hope of caſe, they doe not ſay God hath forſaken, and that the Lord had utterly forgotten them. Its true, they ſee that he is offended, they ſtudy now which way he may be pleaſed, they are ſtoning of their <hi>Achans,</hi> that have made them turne their backs upon their enemies: they apprehend God placable, and that they
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:125569:27"/> may recover, they are purpoſed in all things to follow the advice of their Phiſitions, men by vertue of an order from their Nobles to bind themſelves by promiſe to do according to the law of God.</p>
            <p>O that <hi>England</hi> would make uſe of Iſraels covenant it may he is would prove a divine balſome for the curing of her bleeding wounds: we have as much need to apply this plaiſter, and to take this courſe as ever this people had. Firſt, doe not our ſins hold paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd with theirs, if we goe not before them we follow them at the heels? But who dare ſay this Nation hath bin obſtinate, obdurate againſt the meanes, that ſhe hath bin Idolatrors, yeelding to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious vanities; that ſhe hath bin cruell miſ-uſing and diſpitefully ſtriking the Lords Meſſengers, that ſhe hath bin ingratefull, not rendring thankes according to her mercies, but growne worſe by her glorious favours; or that from the higheſt to the loweſt, from the talleſt Cedars to the meaneſt ſhrubs ſhe is ſhamefully corrupted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I I cannot excuſe her, I muſt lay my hand upon my mouth if I may not bring in an accuſation againſt her<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my conſcience tells me ſhee is guilty. But if of ſins which are of a ſcarlet dye, continually crying like the bloud of <hi>Abel</hi> for the execution of vengeance in the eares of heaven will not move us, yet we thinke the wrath that is gone forth, and the plague is begun amongſt us, by the hurtfull, the oppreſſing and deſtroying ſword ſhould forth-with awake us. O conſider, it is not onely drawn out of the ſcabberd, but it is new ſharpened, and furbuſhed, and given into the hand of the ſtayer: Hath it not alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy cut off many thouſands in the bowels of this our Kingdome? Is not the point thereof ſet againſt all our gates? I wiſh our ruines be not multiplyed, and that it be not yet for a ſorer ſlaughter. Are not our houſes daily plundered, our eſtates violently extorted, our men murdered, our women raviſhed, and our virgins defloured? Liſten and you may heare the mournfull expreſſions, and the dolefull la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations of wounded perſons, nay their groanings gaſping upon the ground for life, wives daily become widowes, and children are bereaved of their fathers, ringing of hands, ſadneſſe of ſpirit, and briniſh teares almoſt in all quarters may become the objects of your fight; O England, England, ihis is the fruit of thy ſin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherefore doth a living man complaine, a man for the puniſhment of his ſins. Lam. 3.39. O now ſearch and try thy waies, and turne againe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:125569:27"/> unto the Lord uſe not complements, perfunctory performances are but as figtree leaves, It is time for thee to beſtir thy ſelfe, lift up thy heart with thy hands to God in the Heavens, thou haſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, thou haſt rebelled, and God hath not pardoned, hee hath ſounded out the Trumpet, ſtricken up the Alarme for war, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his jealouſie to breake forth like fire againſt thee; O ſee now (with thy brethren thy Nobles) what thou canſt doe, covenant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy ſins, it may be thou ſhalt obtaine a covenant of peace with the Lord thy God; I doe not conceive thy eſtate deſperate, be not diſmayed; though God be angry, it may be he will repent him of our evill, he will not retaine his anger for ever; There is yet hope in Iſrael concerning our deliverance, if we would but make a free, a firme, and a faſt covenant with God againſt our luſts. Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra 10.2.3. Tell me, did God ever call forth a people to bind their ſoules in covenant to himſelfe, and not intend their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, covenanting times, are but diſcovering times, and therefore he promiſeth his people, that when he brings them into the bond of covenant, he will purg out the Rebels from amongſt them; and them that tranſgreſſe againſt him; bellow hearted perſons, looſe livers, and prophane creatures, will not willingly meddle with ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred oaths, and holy vowes; And why will hee purge them out? Surely it is for the peace and quiet of his Saints. Peruſe the place, Ezek. 20.37.38. Againe, ſhew me when or where any more ſincerely covenanted with God, and received not mercy from God. Mercy is ſo intayled upon faithfull covenanters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that it cannot be reverſed, Iſa. 56.6.7. They of all others ſhall be brought to his holy mountaine, and made joyfull in his houſe of prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note>But why will God have us thus to enter into a curſe and an oath to ſerve him?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>Firſt, becauſe he knowes, that being once ingaged by a ſacred vow to the acts of holineſſe, our credit, reputation and fidelity lies at the ſtake for our obedience, and that therefore we will be more carefull of our ſelves, and not willingly violate our faith. God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide we ſhould have revolting and rebellious hearts to depart from him. Jerem. 5.23.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe theſe free promiſes iſhuing from an upright heart, are an open mark, and a profeſſed badge of a thankfull ſoule,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:125569:28"/> as theſe evidence our thankes, ſo they ingage us to gratefull expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions upon the receipt of mercies; God would not have us without a ſpur to put us on to duties.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that we may the more ſee the boldneſſe and ſhamefulnes of ſin, like the divell, the more it is oppoſed, the more violently it ſets upon the ſoule. Rom. 7.7.8.9.10.11. Lands, Statutes, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants will not keep it off, were we not put upon vowes, wee ſhould ſcarſe believe this.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that having covenanted, and apprehending our owne weakneſſe in ſins reſiſtance, we may be ſtir'd up with more earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſeeke his ayd. his grace and ſtrength to withſtand it. Pſal. 119.8.26.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, that if we be not carefull to obey, that our owne vowes may riſe up in judgment againſt us, and that upon the breach of them, his juſtice with the more equity may ſeize upon our ſoules. Rom. 3.19.20.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, that by theſe morall covenants our ſpirits may be raiſed up higher, &amp; ſtird up to ſeek after inveſtment in the new covenant, even that which is ratified by the bloud of Chriſt, Galat. 3.21.22,</p>
            <p>But what muſt I covenant againſt?</p>
            <p>Principally againſt thy ſins, temptations, and occaſions that lead unto them, with thoſe God is much offended, and his Name is much diſhonoured. Sinne for a time may be as ſugar under thy tongue, take heed, ſpit it forth, it will prove Ratſ-bane when it comes into thy bowels. Doe not truſt it, it deceives thee, it will op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe thy conſcience, and damne thy ſoule. Vow againſt it.</p>
            <p>Sin made the Divell, who was a moſt glorious Angel an infernall fiend; if thou doe not breake off its communion, it will bring thee in very little better condition; As well as men are conceited of it, it is worſe then Hell, for that is good being prepared by God for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Therefore ſay as St. <hi>Anſelme</hi> ſaid, if ſin and hell were ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, the one on the one ſide, the other on the other; and that I muſt needs goe through one of them, I would rather enter upon hell than ſin, God will aſſuredly keep them from hell, whoſe hearts are thus ſet to keepe themſelves from ſinne.</p>
            <p>But what muſt I vow and covenant to doe?</p>
            <p>Vow to beleeve in God, to hope for eternity of felicity from him,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:125569:28"/> and to live according to his direction God careth not for oyle, for faſts or ſacrifice if they come ſingle without thy ſelfe; that, that hee hath redeemed, that devote and dedicate unto him; vow that thy ſoule ſhall be his Temple, and that whilſt thou liveſt thou wilt ſet forth his praiſe, by a religious, a godly, and a holy life. Thus vow the Jewes.</p>
            <p>But when I have thus covenanted, I am not able to walke accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the whole Law, or perfectly to keep Gods Commands?</p>
            <p>I grant it: But that it may be no diſcouragement to thee, conſider how a Chriſtian is ſaid to keep the Law of the Lord. Firſt, he keeps it imputatively in Chriſt, the Commandement is reputed done, when that is forgiven which is left undone. Secondly, in reſpect of his Will, he having a deſire which is accepted. Thirdly, in regard of endeavour ariſing to frame his life according to the ſtatutes of the Lord. Fourthly, Comparatively in reſpect of others. And laſtly, in regard of the uprightneſſe and integrity of his heart to one Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement as to another, and to all and every one at all times.</p>
            <p>But may I take this laſt Covenant?</p>
            <p>What thinkeſt thou? if it, be againſt ſinne, unleſſe thou keepe it, thou wilt vow againſt it.</p>
            <p>If it be for holineſſe, if thou affect it, thou wilt vow to follow after it.</p>
            <p>If it be for thy Religion, if thou prize it, thou wilt vow to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it.</p>
            <p>If it be to uphold thy liberty, unleſſe thou love bondage, thou wilt vow againſt ſlavery.</p>
            <p>If it be for Law, thou art bound to defend it, for Law is the life of the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>If it be for the defence of the Kingdome, it is for the King; For what is a King without a Kingdome?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou wouldſt not be a Traytor to thy King and Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be for the defence of the Parliament, it is but what before thou wert ingaged unto, and as thou vowed then, thou thus apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, wilt ſurely be content to renew thy vow, never to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious to them whom thou haſt truſted, never to deſert them that have bin faithfull to thy ſelfe, and never to deſtroy thoſe, whom thou haſt choſen as Saviours of thy owne life.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:125569:29"/>
            <p>It is againſt armed papiſts, he that is privy to their tenets, and acquainted with their treacheries; will vow if he can ſhift it, never to come into their bloudy hands.</p>
            <p>It is to remove the evill from before the King; A Loyall Subject would have the Throne eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>But what manner of covenant muſt this be that I muſt make?</p>
            <p>The laſt clauſe of the obſervation tells thee it muſt be a ſure co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, this covenant was left upon Record, it was ſubſcribed, and reſerved unto future times, Nehem. 9, 38. Let ours be like theirs, that if we obſerve it not, it may lie as an evidence againſt us, John. 24.22. And if we keep it that it may teſtifie our faith unto others, and be an incouragement to all ſucceeding ages; Covenanting with God is no horſe-courſing, thou canſt not put it off when thou plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, thou muſt ever keep it, thou muſt all the dayes of thy life ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here unto it, thy intention, thy deliberate purpoſe conjoyned with thy promiſe muſt be, never to deſert it. Deferre not then O <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to covenant with thy God; Enter with thy Nobles into a curſe and an oath to walke ſpeedily, to walke ſtrictly, and to walke conſtantly according to the Law of thy God; Expreſſe thy hope yet with them, (and with theſe Iſraelites) that God hath yet a bleſſed and glorious deliverance for thee.</p>
            <list>
               <head>By</head>
               <item n="1">1<q>
                     <hi> Fleeng to Gods grace, not reſting upon thine owne. demerits.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <bibl>1 Pet. 1.13.</bibl>
               </item>
               <item n="2">2<q>
                     <hi> Vſing the meanes that God hath appointed.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <bibl>Heb. 10.23, 24, 25.</bibl>
               </item>
               <item n="3">3<q>
                     <hi> Reſting upon God, not the meanes, whether he workes with it, or without it,</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <bibl>Eſter 4.14.</bibl>
               </item>
               <item n="4">4<q>
                     <hi> Proteſting againſt ſin, and in all things to pleaſe his majeſty.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <bibl>1 Iohn 3.3.</bibl>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>Dloria Deo.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Perlegi hunc tractatum, proto, et in princendum judico. <hi>In. Crawford. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:125569:29"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
